<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Telemark | Leftbound]]></title>
  <link href="http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/categories/telemark/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://leftbound.com/leftbound/"/>
  <updated>2019-08-13T00:57:39+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://leftbound.com/leftbound/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Joni Palomäki]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[joni@leftbound.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Road Trip in the North]]></title>
    <link href="http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2016/11/08/Road-Trip-In-The-North/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-08T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2016/11/08/Road-Trip-In-The-North</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Espoo all powdery white and <a href="http://skiexpo.messukeskushelsinki.fi">Skiexpo</a> just finished, it is due time to start shifting focus to the winter. And what better way to get that started, than looking back at the last season&rsquo;s ventures, for buzz and inspiration.</p>

<p>Season 2015/2016 was extremely good for me, right from the very start. Opening the season already early December, in <a href="http://www.ruka.fi">Ruka</a>, joining a 3-day telemark boot camp organized specifically for our small group, was the perfect kick off. It was facilitated by <a href="http://ski.ruka.fi/en/skischool">Ruka Ski School</a>, with Martti Kontula as the instructor. Lucky with the weather, we even got some fresh powder, and the boot camp was both humbling and educational. Videos shot during the camp were ruthless in their honesty, but were a great way to highlight and discuss improvement areas in one&rsquo;s form and technique. Tips, ideas and both physical and mental exercises were shared, to carry the teachings through the season.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/30768702621/in/album-72157676300622745/" title="Máttačorru ridge"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/6/5348/30768702621_4d1868466c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Máttačorru ridge"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Plenty of turns followed that great start, with one of the memorable adventures being a road trip to the Lyngen alps, and Northern Sweden, in early April. Not a stranger to the mountains of Norway, having done summer tour in the glaciers near <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lyngseidet">Lyngseidet</a>, climbed rock in the magic islands of <a href="https://27crags.com/areas/lofoten#68.31410200000002,15.781832812499943,8z,">Lofoten</a> and <a href="http://www.ukclimbing.com/articles/page.php?id=152">ice in Rjukan</a>, I have for long wanted to explore also the ski touring possibilities around the fjords of Norway. So when an opportunity came to plan and execute a road trip in those surroundings, on a camper, no second thoughts were given.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/30221194833/in/album-72157676300622745/" title="Stopover"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5608/30221194833_19e36afd77_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Stopover"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s a long way across the country, in total some 1400 kilometers from Espoo to the Tamok valley in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Balsfjord">Balsfjord</a>, which was the first destination on our loosely planned tour. A great location for ski touring, the 25 kilometer long valley has everything from wide open lines on mellow slopes to steep walls and gnarly chutes. We parked the camper at the &lsquo;Huset&rsquo;, a legendary basecamp at the foot of mountains, ran by Aadne Olsrud. An old community hall resurrected, it has all the basic amenities to relax and recover after a day in the mountains. While we slept and cooked in the camper, we paid a small fee to use the facilities while there. Evening of arrival was spent over a map and a guidebook, planning, with a keen eye on the weather forecast which wasn&rsquo;t very promising for the next few days.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/30224585774/in/dateposted/" title="#pelastetaantalvet"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/6/5460/30224585774_a944e9af6a_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="#pelastetaantalvet"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/30555627870/in/photostream/" title="Tamok valley seen from half way up Sjufellet"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/6/5461/30555627870_1c75d70bd9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Tamok valley seen from half way up Sjufellet"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Our chosen tour took us next morning to Sjufjellet, a classic peak in the area. Despite the special micro climate which typically makes Tamok more snow-sure than the surrounding valleys, at this time snow was relatively scarse at the valley, but we hoped to find a good run higher up regardless. Skinning up, we transitioned from wet slush into a hardpack, reaching the soft stuff some one thirds up on the face of the Seven. Despite the overcast and clouds hanging low, the visibility remained good on the way up, with a perfectly timed opening in the sky, when we reached the summit after some 900 meters of vertical climbing. Enjoying the views around us, we took a short break. Weather starting to close in again, we headed downhill, and had a great powder run on the upper slopes, cruising down. Visibility remaining good, as we tracked back the short traverse and descended back to the valley. A great first run for the trip!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/30856626165/in/photostream/" title="Back in the Tamok valley"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/6/5619/30856626165_5cb6c1ebf6_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Back in the Tamok valley"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>We stayed for another night, but unfortunately the weather was closing in on us, and we decided to hit the road again next morning, after consulting few maps, guidebooks and <a href="http://www.yr.no">yr.no</a>. Northbound again, we drove to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lyngseidet">Lyngseidet</a>. Arriving there early afternoon, weather was indeed looking a lot better, with a much lighter overcast with few openings in the horizon. Plenty of day left, we decided to take a shot at summiting Kavrintinden, to ski down a steep bowl just below the summit, and cruise down back to the town. Tour started right above Lyngseidet, and followed a well-trodden path through the woods, bringing us without on to the higher, more open terrain. On the way up we awed the surrounding mountains and the fjord down behind us.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/30555636010/in/photostream/" title="Lyngenfjord"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/6/5466/30555636010_4a334fa0eb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Lyngenfjord"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Higher up, it got quite steep, and at times, especially on wind-packed snow, I was pushing the limits of my climbing skins, not having a pair of ski crampons (none exists for my NTN bindings). On the soft stuff, things were naturally a whole lot easier. Snowpack was stable, and we could continue at ease, finally reaching the summit ridge. Entering the ridge after some 1300 meters of climbing, the wind blowing from the other side caught us, so we hurried across it, and took shelter just below the summit. We decided to skip hiking the last 5 minutes to the summit above, but instead took a short break and watched the weather miracly starting to clear out completely. Dropping into the bowl, a clumpy ride at first, exiting the steepest section it was pure joy on the way down. We carved turns in untouched powder snow, sun on our backs, unfrozen fjord underneath us. It&rsquo;s only in places like Lyngen, where you get this kind of spectacular views no camera can truly capture.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/30221195993/in/album-72157676300622745/" title="Lyngenfjord and Lyngseidet"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5547/30221195993_033bbbbf68_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Lyngenfjord and Lyngseidet"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/30740244702/in/album-72157676300622745/" title="Kavringtinden"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/6/5584/30740244702_437db8c0ef_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Kavringtinden"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>While we got lucky with the weather window, it did not hold for long, and so we decided to move on again, this time towards <a href="http://www.visitnarvik.com/Home">Narvik</a>. Next day, we were considering skiing in the Narvik fell for half a day or so, upon arrival, but since the visibility higher up was bad, there was no point. So we enjoyed a day off and while stocking up supplies, we again hunched over a map and decided to head over to a valley south from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beisfjord">Beisfjord</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/30221189583/in/album-72157676300622745/" title="On the beach near Narvik"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/6/5615/30221189583_55736cfd0c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="On the beach near Narvik"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Driving there on a meandering backroad, it started to snow heavily, and in couple of hours, there were some 20 centimeters of fresh snow accumulated. We camped near a beautiful valley lake with a high mountain skyline all around.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/30221207493/in/album-72157676300622745/" title="Near Beisfjord"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/6/5609/30221207493_7ba4b54b87_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Near Beisfjord"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/30221212873/in/album-72157676300622745/" title="Serene lake"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5553/30221212873_89d0f021b9_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Serene lake"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Next morning, again with an overcast, we started our tour from the valley, heading towards Tverrdalsfjellet and Máttačorru. First hour or so we had the skis on our backs, scrambling up a steep rock garden, following a now mostly hidden stream running down from the mountains. Reaching the treeline, and the valley higher up, weather again started to clear up. Sun shone on us sporadically, while we continued to skin up. Once we reached the gulley we had planned to explore, we soon had our skis on our backs again, as we inched up the steep gully, closely monitoring the snowpack for any instability. Due to the fresh snowfall, there was a good amount of fluffy snow on top of a harder layer of old snow, well compacted. Examining the snowpack, we found no alarming weak layers that could potentially fail when loaded.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/30555635250/in/album-72157676300622745/" title="Scrambling"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/6/5731/30555635250_487dc82a1c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Scrambling"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/30555641280/in/album-72157676300622745/" title="River unseen"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/6/5604/30555641280_0ff6b10183_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="River unseen"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/30820095376/in/album-72157676300622745/" title="Traversing"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/6/5477/30820095376_7140c177d2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Traversing"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Reaching the top of the gulley, we were met by astounding views all around. Skies having completely cleared up on our climb up, with no wind to speak off, we were in no hurry to head back, but instead spent few hours touring the upper range and checking the Máttačorru traverse that would have been interesting, had we brought some climbing equipment with us. We skinned up and skied down smaller contours, and basked in the sun. We couldn&rsquo;t believe how lucky we again had gotten with the weather window. Forecast had indicated weather could clear a bit towards the afternoon, but to our pleasant surprise, it turned into a blue bird!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/30221223703/in/album-72157676300622745/" title="Tverrdalsfjellet"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/6/5542/30221223703_605ba73548_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Tverrdalsfjellet"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/30820124196/in/album-72157676300622745/" title="Snow!"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/6/5819/30820124196_bf8ce905e0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Snow!"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>When it was time to head back down, after a total of 1500 meters of climbing, we found ourselves cruising down the steep gulley, enjoying the perfect soft snow. Apart from a few shouts of awe and joy on the way down, all sounds were muffled by the layer of fresh powder.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/30221214093/in/album-72157676300622745/" title="This is it"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/6/5808/30221214093_694cb1a351_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="This is it"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/30856668975/in/album-72157676300622745/" title="Down the couloir, on the lower third"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/6/5579/30856668975_9fb7eb781d_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Down the couloir, on the lower third"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/30820127246/in/album-72157676300622745/" title="Ascent/descent to Tverrdalsfjellet"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/6/5566/30820127246_8626048050_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ascent/descent to Tverrdalsfjellet"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>A great tour under the belt, but weather closing in on us again (you see a pattern here already?), we moved on again and left Norway, barely. Our next stop was at <a href="http://riksgransen.se">Riksgränsen</a>, a ski resort just on the border of Sweden and Norway. It was only few weeks I had been there last time (more about that trip later in this blog), ski touring, but this time it served as a place to recover and resupply for a day. I also did some kite skiing, as I had brought the gear with me, should an opportunity like this arise. Weather remained reasonable throughout the day, though windy (hence the kite) and overcast.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/30830176616/in/album-72157676300622745/" title="Låktatjåkka parking"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/6/5602/30830176616_7ec9bc8df3_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Låktatjåkka parking"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Our next, and the road trip&rsquo;s final tour was decided to be in the vicinity of Låktatjåkka. Parking overnight on the side of the road, on a narrow turnout, ensured an early start straight from the camper.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/30820087426/in/album-72157676300622745/" title="Reindeers"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/6/5774/30820087426_e6d038fa6e_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Reindeers"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Mother nature agreed once more, and soon after we had started our way up next morning, we were again greeted the sun, peeping behind the quickly dissipating clouds. Skinning up we took note of areas with soft powder, and saw a herd of reindeers on the lower slopes, passing them from a distance. Once we were up in the valley, through which one also travels to the Låktatjåkkastugan (a mountain hut that can serve as a basecamp for ski touring in the area), we took a right turn, and started climbing up a saddle that would lead us towards <a href="http://sn%C3%B6s%C3%A4ker.se/topptur/abisko-bjorkliden-riksgransen/geargecorru/">Geargecorru</a> summit. Snow was partially wind packed, with soft spots in more sheltered zones, before we reached the top plateau. Completely wind blown and icy, with lots of rocks visible, we gave up on the idea of summiting as pointless, perhaps 200 vertical meters before the summit, and instead continued down south to explore the leeside slopes for some powder turns.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/30555647720/in/album-72157676300622745/" title="Avalanche"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/6/5523/30555647720_7a6d2c8d52_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Avalanche"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Not surprisingly, the snow was much better on that side, and we had good runs  with plenty of soft powder. We saw some traces of avalanches on some of the steep walls nearby and carefully kept on evaluating the conditions for safe skiing. Guidebook we used had warned about hazardous exits from the summit plateau, should one wish to ski down one of the steep couloirs that connect to the valley between the mountains. Despite our careful map reading and good visibility, approach to what we thought was the correct chute, from above over a convex slope, met a dead end. A large drop down below and icy traverse on both sides, had us climbing straight up, skis on our backs. Taking note of the surprisingly icy conditions on that part of the mountain, instead of traversing a bit further, we decided we would be better off taking the long cruise back, following our ascent route from the valley. A smart choice in the end, it was a nice run back to the camper in mixed snow of powder, hard pack and crud.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/30221208343/in/album-72157676300622745/" title="Exiting a dead end"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/6/5773/30221208343_381e671cc0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Exiting a dead end"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>All good things come to an end, and thrilled about how things had turned out throughout the week, we started the long journey back home. As we had had to make and change plans on the fly, judging the weather and the prevailing conditions in the mountains as we went, having a camper with us turned out to be a trip saver. Being able to move with (or run from) the weather allowed us to take the most out of what nature chose to offer. I can highly recommend a similar tour, and a camper as the moving basecamp. For this trip, there were just two of us, and despite I&rsquo;ve referred to only &lsquo;skiing&rsquo; above (for simplicity), my friend was actually on snowboard, a splitted one, as you can see from the pictures. This worked well, as skinning up we had a similar brisk pace and a team of two keeps thing simple, yet safe enough. Splitboard seemed to work fine for most part, though steep traverses on short but wide halves was definitely more strenuous, especially on hard pack. Of course snowboard is superbly good on powder, so for the extra effort, there is a reward in the end. I use telemark skis myself, NTN&rsquo;s (<a href="http://www.rottefella.com/product/freedom/">Rottefella Freedom</a>) and medium width, lightweight skis (<a href="http://skimo.co/black-diamond-carbon-aspect-skis">Black Diamond Carbon Aspect</a>), that worked perfectly throughout the season.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/30820121096/in/album-72157676300622745/" title="Skis off"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/6/5799/30820121096_37931838f4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Skis off"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>As I&rsquo;ve mentioned, we used maps and guidebooks to make plans on the go. Depending where in northern Norway or Sweden you head to, you might find the following guidebooks useful:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.ffshop.no/touring-troms-p-1246.html?osCsid=b932ago0tpvgtesaqoasdsjo24">Ski Touring in Troms</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.ffshop.no/toppturer-norge-p-918.html">Toppturer i Norge</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.topptur.nu/books.asp?pid=1&amp;language=2">Topptur Narvik-Riksgränsen-Björkliden-Abisko</a> (discontinued, but a great book if you can find one)</li>
</ul>


<p>Also few web resources, such as <a href="http://kugo.no">Kugo.no</a> and <a href="http://sn%C3%B6s%C3%A4ker.se">Snösäker.se</a>, are extremely useful for planning purposes.</p>

<p>&#10095;&#10095; Flickr album (with more photos): <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/albums/72157676300622745/with/30820124196/">Road Trip in the North</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Järvsö - 3700 dm.ö.h]]></title>
    <link href="http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2016/03/03/Jarvso-3700-Dmoh/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-03T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2016/03/03/Jarvso-3700-Dmoh</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For the last three winters in a row, our family&rsquo;s winter vacation (school&rsquo;s out for week 8) has taken us to <a href="http://www.are360.com/en/">Åre</a>, in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/J%C3%A4mtland_County">Jämtland</a>. Main reason we have been lately opting to go to Sweden, instead of heading up north in Finland, is the ease of travel, requiring lot less driving. Each time we&rsquo;ve driven there, a small town called Järvsö has been passed, just before Ljusdal, and each time we&rsquo;ve wondered out loud, what kind of resort that would be.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/28741122140/in/album-72157665251303531/" title="Untitled"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/9/8445/28741122140_3f8520cf75_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Untitled"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Come this spring, we recalled Järvsö and after checking it online and learning there was a new ski-in/ski-out hotel, <a href="http://www.bergshotellet.se">Bergshotellet</a>, built during 2015 and now open for the first season - we quickly deciced to skip Åre this year, and go finally check this place out. This year we had also other commitments for the vacation days, so similar to our <a href="http://leftbound.com/blog/2016/02/02/Hemavan-On-Skis/">Hemavan trip</a> at the end of the year, we decided three full skiing days would do. A familiar route, we chose again to cross the Baltic Sea on <a href="http://www.tallinksilja.fi/">Tallink Silja</a> ferries, this time Silja Symphony, which had a nice new sushi restaurant, Sushi &amp; Co. There are always shows on these boats, typically 2-3 during the evening (aerobatics, music, dancing and whatnot), but this time there was a bonus gig, as one of the coveted pop artists in Finland at the moment, <a href="http://petoonirti.com">Antti Tuisku</a>, was starting a two-week tour on the boat, and we got to see the first one. Not my kind of music, I must say, but live performances are always fun to watch, with the rest of the crowd.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/28922326262/in/album-72157665251303531/" title="Untitled"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/9/8416/28922326262_ec20e42b82_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Untitled"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/28922326902/in/album-72157665251303531/" title="Untitled"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/9/8409/28922326902_d4f0cf9582_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Untitled"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Arriving to Stockholm next morning and only about 320 kilometers to drive to Järvsö, we spent few ours roaming the city, and started towards Järvsö early afternoon. We quickly arrived to Tönnebro on E4 and diverted inlands towards Ljusdal, reaching our destination only after four hours of driving.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/28994585326/in/album-72157665251303531/" title="Untitled"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/9/8041/28994585326_804cf17b1b_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Untitled"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Arriving at the hotel late in the evening, we had a dinner at the <a href="http://www.bergshotellet.se/bergskrogen">Bergskrogen</a>, to not have to go searching for a restaurant downtown. And as the restaurant turned out to be very good, we dined there again (they also have a great lunch buffé), and naturally had breakfast there every morning. Everything brand new, lots of wood was used as building material, and for decoration and furniture. Following a kind of eco-friendly approach, the restaurant for example sources much of the incredients locally, makes their own bread, and so on. It was a fantastic place to stay in, must say!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/29027416795/in/album-72157665251303531/" title="Untitled"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/9/8107/29027416795_ac7146dfd7_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Untitled"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>A ski-in/ski-out hotel, we had a kids slope, and a platter lift, just in front of the hotel, with a conveyor-belt style skilift also for the small sledding hill on the side (with small snow scoots to borrow at the hotel). And a nice movable stall serving fresh crepés and beverages.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/29027387495/in/album-72157665251303531/" title="Untitled"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/9/8524/29027387495_37a18102b0_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Untitled"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a href="http://jarvso.se">Järvsö</a> ski resort has two sides - south side, where the hotel is at, and north, where majority of the slopes are. As the resort is not very big, all slopes are accessible from either side, connected on the top, at 3700 decimeters over the sea, as they playfully state on the top lift station. Resort puts a lot of effort into maintaining the piste, and all the slopes are prepared each day, as they close at 16:30 (except on Tuesday and Thursday, when there&rsquo;s night skiing on the north side from 18:00 to 20:30). During our stay, the slopes were all in excellent condition, and while there is no real off piste to speak of (some forest trails and bike paths to run, but there wasn&rsquo;t that much snow and terrain is thick and rocky), we had a blast skiing in the sun for all three days. Especially the slopes number 12, 13 and 15 were our favorites, as well as number 3 on the south side.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/28741124530/in/album-72157665251303531/" title="Untitled"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/9/8770/28741124530_ebfa429a8b_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Untitled"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/28741123270/in/album-72157665251303531/" title="Untitled"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/9/8222/28741123270_13d46737da_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Untitled"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>In the area, just behind the hotel, there is also a zoo, <a href="http://www.jarvzoo.se">Järvzoo</a>. In there, built on the slopes just next to the piste, a range of Nordic animals can be viewed in their natural environment (considering it&rsquo;s still a zoo). A wooden walkway leads through it (accessible also by wheelchair), forming a loop roughly 3 kilometers in length. While the zoo is open only until 15:00 during winter season, one can enter just before that, and spend as long as needed inside - this is also what we did, as we first had a day&rsquo;s worth of skiing bagged, and then entered the zoo just before closing time.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/28410008263/in/album-72157665251303531/" title="Untitled"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/9/8318/28410008263_d87693ebf4_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Untitled"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I hoped to get a glimpse of were wolves, wolverines and lynxes, and got plenty of good views of all but the last, as lynxes could not be found in the plain daylight. I recommend bringing binoculars, as the encloses are relatively large (which is good), so you will get better views with them. I tried to take a few photos through my Leica Ultravid 8X25 binoculars, but could not really get them sharp, handheld and not attached together in any way.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/28922346912/in/album-72157665251303531/" title="Untitled"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8385/28922346912_348f0ff1e2_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Untitled"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>While it was nice to see those animals live, especially wolves which I followed for a long time, the really nice surprise came in the evening. It was thursday, so the north side had the night skiing ongoing. Rather than taking the free bus transfer to the other side, I opted to skin up in the dark, and ski a few laps on the illuminated slopes on the other side, before skiing back down to the hotel from the top, equipped with a headlamp.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/28951317851/in/album-72157665251303531/" title="Untitled"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/9/8354/28951317851_1eaaccfd60_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Untitled"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Skinning up, I could listen the owls calling in the dark - there were several types of owls in the zoo, I think what I heard was the long-eared owl. Then, stopping to view the surroundings under the full moon, I saw a wolf emerging from the woods behind and downhill of me, and lope across the piste, to disappear into the woods again. This was the first time I&rsquo;ve seen a wolf run free, and though I had just been viewing a pack of them inside the zoo, it was a cool bonus for the evening&rsquo;s little ski tour!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/28922353112/in/album-72157665251303531/" title="Untitled"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8112/28922353112_54f67a8f0e_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Untitled"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>On the morning of departure, I used the last opportunity to get some more mileage on skins, and did another &lsquo;topptur&rsquo; after breakfast, skinning up the long meandering blue piste and across the forest, to the top, for the very last run. During our stay I had only seen few other people on telemark skis, and now me ski touring there on such gear in bright daylight triggered a few smiles and thumbs up on the way up. A perfect ending for a nice vacation, glad we chose Järvsö as our destination, let&rsquo;s see if we&rsquo;ll make another visit (or a stop) here sometime. I can warmly recommend this resort, and the hotel, especially if you travel with kids, even very small ones. Outside the Bergskrogen, there&rsquo;re several other good restaurants to go to - check especially the cozy <a href="http://www.condis.se">Condis Bar &amp; Kök</a>. And lots of cottages as well! Note though that Järvsö is often fully booked, also why the new hotel was welcomed to the area, so book on time.</p>

<p>&#10095;&#10095; Flickr album (with more photos): <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/albums/72157665251303531">Järvsö - 3700 dm.ö.h</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hemavan on Skis]]></title>
    <link href="http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2016/02/02/Hemavan-On-Skis/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-02T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2016/02/02/Hemavan-On-Skis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With Christmas vacations typically spent around southern Ostrobothnia, from where our families are, many times we&rsquo;ve been discussing to free up a few days around Christmas and/or New Year and travel across kvarken to ski in the Swedish fells. While typically we dash through bunch of friends and relatives during those days, which is great but also hectic and consuming, we welcomed a late reservation through booking.com into <a href="http://www.hemavansfjallcenter.se">Hemavans Fjällcenter</a>, a <a href="https://www.svenskaturistforeningen.se">Svenska Turistföreningen (STF)</a> facility. Once confirmed, we booked the ferry across the kvarken, from Vaasa to Umeå, nowadays operated by <a href="http://www.wasaline.com/en/">Wasaline</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/28742496960/in/photostream/" title="On the ferry to Umeå"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8096/28742496960_113669dc70_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1536" alt="On the ferry to Umeå"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Come Boxing Day, we boarded the ferry in Vaasa, with heavy winds (around 20 meters per second) pounding the harbor. Needless to say the journey across was on rough seas, but as the distance is quite short, it took only about four hours, until we docked in Umeå.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/28742496960/in/dateposted/" title="On the ferry to Umeå"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8096/28742496960_113669dc70_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1536" alt="On the ferry to Umeå"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Although the distance between Umeå and Hemavan is only about 380 kilometers, the road conditions were quite tough on our trip, with much of it being on iced up roads, which slowed us down a bit. With friction tires under the car, I didn&rsquo;t want to push it, but rather arrive a bit later, but without incidents, to Hemavan. We had no rush as the skiing would only start the next day.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/28742498520/in/photostream/" title="Lift to the high zone"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8792/28742498520_bc508b9856_k.jpg" width="1536" height="2048" alt="Lift to the high zone"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Hemavan Fjällcenter is a cozy guesthouse-like hotel/hostel, with several one-floor buildings with rooms and facilities. In addition to the hotel room we stayed in, there&rsquo;s also an option for room with just beds and a faucet - toilets and showers, and kitchen, would then be shared. We originally had booked the latter option, but closer to the trip, upgraded to a hotel room with a very small fee. We ended up staying in building Renen, opposite the main building, which had been just refurbished. The only thing we would have liked to have was a dryer and a locker for skis, to stash the wet gear after the day - now we just had to fill up the bathroom. Breakfast was served in the main building and was top notch - same goes for the dinner buffé we had on our arrival night. Sadly that was the only time we could enjoy it, as it did not run during the weekdays, at this time of the year.</p>

<p>Fjällcenter, as it turned out, is THE place for people riding snowmobiles. Tracks start at the backdoor, and every morning there were tens and tens of snowmobiles revving the engines at the yard and hitting the extensive trail network around Hemavan-Tärnaby region. Skiers, although that week in minority, have it almost as good, with only a short walk from the Fjällcenter to the nearest lift station (Centrumliften) - no car was needed during our stay to get in and out of the slopes.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/28742500360/in/photostream/" title="Mom and dad"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8611/28742500360_dbc1e77282_k.jpg" width="1536" height="2048" alt="Mom and dad"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>We got really lucky with the weather, despite the high winds preceding. There had been a good dump of snow couple of days before, and while during our first day the high zone (lifts) was closed due to wind, the lower zone offered superb skiing, on and off piste, with few of the closed (but roughly prepared before the snow fall) piste having a knee plus deep powder to plow all day. No crowd meant no queuing for the lifts, and virgin powder was easily found until day&rsquo;s end, taking new lines each round.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/28408476744/in/photostream/" title="Powder!"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8506/28408476744_4619d44654_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1536" alt="Powder!"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Next day the wind had calmed down up in the fells, and the high zone lifts were opened. As the high zone had been closed since the snow fall, snow was again untouched and with vast plateau above the treeline to zigzag, we did not run out of powder that day either. My daughter hadn&rsquo;t really skied off piste (or powder) before this trip, but now she was going at it second day in a row, not wanting to cross the prepared piste, I think she&rsquo;s hooked for good!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/28742499920/in/photostream/" title="Soft terrain ahead"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8165/28742499920_d64e9afcaf_k.jpg" width="1536" height="2048" alt="Soft terrain ahead"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Third day, and our last day offered more of the same, but the lower zone now prepared all across, we stayed most on the high zone, finding remaining patches of untouched snow, which was still soft at the treeline and below, while it had started to pack and harden higher up. From above the treeline, traversing to skiers right, there&rsquo;s very good skiing in the woods, as I learned from a local I met in the lift - snow was fluffy and plentiful also there. I had a friend who came over to Hemavan on our last day, so we had few runs together and few folköl&rsquo;s in the neat new <a href="http://www2.hemavantarnaby.se/sv/mat-dryck/a1043743/bj%C3%B6rk-topprestaurang-fj%C3%A4llbar/detaljer?filter=c%3D12096">Björk</a> restaurant, up on the fell (top of the Sollkatsliften).</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/29028796285/in/photostream/" title="Sun down low"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/9/8038/29028796285_8835c2cc77_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Sun down low"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After three great days of skiing, our legs were toast, so a break from skiing was due. This time, it had also come time to end our short vacation and head back to Umeå and across the, again stormy, seas back to Finland, to celebrate New Year.</p>

<p><a href="http://hemavantarnaby.se/oppettider-och-pistkarta-hemavans-skidsystem/">Hemavan</a> resort did not leave much to desire, it was pretty much what we expected and wanted - Mellow slopes with easy access off piste and good skiing in general. The town, if you can call it that, is very small, a cluster of houses with a grocery store and few restaurants, some of which were surprisingly closed during our stay, and opening up only for the New Year. The days between Christmas and New Year are low key, so expect no crowd - great! Same goes for the week 8 (protip!), the winter vacation week at schools in southern Finland.</p>

<p>One of the additional bonuses, though only available from February onwards, is the very affordable heli-skiing, taking skiers to the nearby fells for very a reasonable fee. The booking is also made easy and practical. You call to a number, stating when you are in the area and available (non-binding), and you will be notified when a group is formed and conditions allow to fly, typically the previous day. As we all liked the place a lot, we&rsquo;ll certainly be back, and hopefully then will be able to give a try that heli-skiing as well!</p>

<p>Sometimes it&rsquo;s good to leave the camera behind and simply enjoy the views, rather than trying to make digital copies of them. This trip was one of such for me, and I barely pulled out the camera to grab a photo. Photos featured in this post are hence mostly from my daughter&rsquo;s iPhone.</p>

<p>&#10095;&#10095; Flickr album: <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/albums/72157671376931870">Hemavan on Skis</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
