<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Electronics | Leftbound]]></title>
  <link href="http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/categories/electronics/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://leftbound.com/leftbound/"/>
  <updated>2019-08-13T00:37:54+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://leftbound.com/leftbound/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Joni Palomäki]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[joni@leftbound.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Garmin Fēnix 3]]></title>
    <link href="http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2015/05/07/Garmin-Fe%CC%84nix-3/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-07T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2015/05/07/Garmin-Fēnix-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A big fan of utility watches, I have always had a keen eye on new innovative products that are entering the market, especially if they have any potential to be a game changer when it comes to form and/or function. Wristop computers, or wearable smart devices if you will, have come a long way from the launch of of the world&rsquo;s first outdoor watch Suunto Vector back in 1998, packing today an impressive amount of functions for such small gadgets. For me, Suunto, Polar and Garmin are the companies that have been pushing the envelope through the generations of products, and over the last 15 years, I have been happily using products such as the Vector, T6- and Ambit-series from Suunto, S-series bicycle watches from Polar and Edge bike computers from Garmin. While the physical products themselves have improved over time with better design and use of materials such as light composites, stainless steel and mineral and sapphire glass, so have also the software products that are paramount for this type of smart devices. Evolved from executables running on your desktop computer, at times only on Windows OS, today we see them gone all cloudy and social, which is all very welcome, if not completely trouble-free.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157650104285723"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8728/17219706959_c99cbd9fdc_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>As a long time user of Suunto watches, lately the <a href="http://www.suunto.com/en-GB/Sports-Watch-Collections/Suunto-Connected-Family-with-Ambit3/">Ambit</a> series, I had been following the launch of the fēnix wristop devices with interest. While the first two generations were entering the market, I kept on using my Ambit2, and later Ambit3, with essentially the same features and functions in somewhat more elegant package. Subjective of course, and up to your personal preferences, using these smart watches, day in and day out, I appreciated the less utilitarian looks of especially the Sapphire versions of Ambit. I was however rather underwhelmed by the marginal improvements over the Ambit generations and disappointed with <a href="http://www.movescount.com/">Movescount</a>, coming from the old Training Manager, I was waiting for something better to come by.</p>

<iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/115994515" width="500" height="281" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>The introduction of <a href="http://fenix3.garmin.com/en-GB/">fēnix 3</a> in <a href="http://www.cesweb.org">CES</a> this year raised a lot of positive buzz, with Garmin taking a big leap both in terms of design and functionality, launching a product that was not only, in my opinion, head and shoulders above its predecessor, but one that could outplay the current competition. Eager to find this out myself, Garmin offered me an opportunity to test and review the fēnix 3, and for a month now, I have been putting it to the test, finding out just what this wearable smart device is made of.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157650104285723"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7776/17379931026_514cfa2b9f_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>From what I can tell so far, I do think it belongs to the top tier, packing innovative ideas that make others appear outmoded. But there is more to it, so read on to find all about it. As usual I will be taking here a more hands on approach, with handpicked highlights and focus points. Hence I will not be discussing the <a href="https://buy.garmin.com/en-GB/GB/outdoor/wrist-worn/fenix-3/prod160512.html">specifications</a> in detail, nor will I be <a href="http://www.dcrainmaker.com/2015/03/garmin-fenix3-detailed-review.html">opening the box</a> with you, but I do intend to share with you my honest views and opinions about the product.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157650104285723"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5455/16785647113_8041cf78e3_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>The model I got for testing is the <a href="https://buy.garmin.com/en-US/US/on-the-trail/wrist-worn/fenix-3/prod160512.html">Silver Performance Bundle</a>, including a <a href="https://buy.garmin.com/en-US/US/shop-by-accessories/fitness-sensors/hrm-run-/prod133715.html">HRM-Run</a> which in addition to accurately measuring your heart rate, also sports an accelerometer for additional running metrics. Compared to the top of the line <a href="https://buy.garmin.com/en-US/US/on-the-trail/wrist-worn/fenix-3-sapphire-with-metal-band/prod516264.html">Sapphire</a> version, it lacks the sapphire glass display and stainless steel wrist band. While the first is something I have learned to appreciate on my last two Ambit watches, the mineral glass does seem very hard wearing and so far I have not been able to get a single scratch on it, despite being knocked around. The stainless steel bezel, effectively the new omni-directional EXO antenna, is both elegant and hard wearing, and ages a lot better than for example anodized aluminum alloy.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157650104285723"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8705/17219706459_bbbb69f735_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>As the watch came with a bright red band, I wanted also something less obtrusive to wear around office. Garmin offers optional <a href="https://buy.garmin.com/en-US/US/shop-by-accessories/bands/fenix-3-bands/prod507506.html">bands for fēnix 3</a>, but as at the time they were hard to come by in black, I instead purchased an interchangeable fēnix 2 band. Bands are attached with torx screws that are of different size (T10 on 2 versus T6 on 3), and while the spare comes with a pair of T10 screwdrivers, make sure you also have a pair of T6&rsquo;s for the original band, as you will be reusing its pin and screws. Fēnix 2 band has a non-slip checker texture and a polished stainless steel buckle that I much prefer over the all black fēnix 3 band.</p>

<p>Taking the watch into use was a breeze, device walking you through some of the basic parameters required - units, height, weight and so on. I switched the language to Finnish, connected the device to my MacBook Pro with the provided USB dock, and installed the connectivity utility, Garmin Express. Once connected, I was able to quickly check for firmware updates, and shortly after had the watch fully up to date and ready to use. I have so far received two updates to the watch, latest one on April 21. Current version, 3.20, as well as the ones preceding it have been performing flawlessly, in other words I have not experienced any erratic behavior or freezing, nor have I had to reset the device at any time.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157650104285723"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7758/17219707409_6868d2c325_z.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Garmin Express, aside of managing software updates and data transfer between the watch and Garmin Connect, can also be used to manage Apps on the device. I appreciate the fact that all the settings can be changed in the device itself, even on the go, but for bulk removal (or download) of apps, Garmin Connect is quicker, also to check the available storage space on your device, with maximum of 16 Apps or 512 kB allowed. A complex watch face for example takes about 40 kB.</p>

<p>Having used Garmin devices earlier, I was already familiar with Garmin Connect, the online portal for storage and statistical analysis of your data, and a lot more, which since I last time had logged in had been completely overhauled. Using Safari, I was able to log in without problems, finding the polished interface clean and fully localized, easy to navigate. Packed with various views to your activity (and personal) data, the interface is easily customized to your liking, allowing you to add and remove items as you wish, on each screen tab. After using the very basic and closed Movescount for couple of years, at first Garmin Connect felt even a bit exhausting, in comparison, but I quickly came in terms with it, appreciating the freedom to choose how I view my data. As an example, I rotate the chains on my bike every 1000 kilometers or so, to get more out of the complete drive train. For this purpose, being able to log that in and pull a report over a specific time frame, not just the typical &lsquo;past week&rsquo; or &lsquo;past month&rsquo; summaries, as a matter-of-fact odometer is essential. Unlike in Movescount where I have been struggling for example with this task exactly, in Garmin Connect this is just a matter of opening a summary report and choosing the time frame and an activity filter. Simple, just as it should be!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157650104285723"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8820/17198465647_e2fcaf583d_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>As an everyday wearable, fēnix 3 has proved to be a great companion. I especially like the fact that it tracks movement throughout the day, step counter included, and promptly reminds me during the day to stand up from my desk and move around. Vibration alerts ensure quiet but effective notifications and allow you to turn off all the random blips and beeps otherwise needed, including watch alarm. Watch face can be modified with few built in options and more can be downloaded from <a href="https://apps.garmin.com/">Connect IQ store</a>, which I will be discussing more later. Also found from the store, I am currently using <a href="https://apps.garmin.com/en-GB/apps/54575a68-e41e-41bc-8c82-12960ae9e45a">Simple Black</a> by usul_, displaying time, date, step counter and remaining battery life in percentage.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157650104285723"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8829/17218347800_de99b456d5_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Downloading the Connect Mobile application for my iPhone from the App Store, installation of said watch faces (and other Connect IQ Apps) is simple, and with bluetooth enabled on the smart phone, one can lock on to additional resources such as weather details, notifications (calls, SMS, email and social media), calendar and for example music controls over your smart phone. Reading notifications in the watch, I have not experienced any formatting issues with the different type of notifications. Music controls on the other hand only work within the Music app, which is a pity for us Spotify users. This is, as far as I know, more of Apple&rsquo;s problem, so Android users might have better luck with it. I am personally more inclined to use activity related widgets and do not actively use for example the weather or calendar widget. Depending on your personal preferences, it is however easy to hide any redundant widget, or download new ones from Connect IQ.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157650104285723"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8796/17219709389_0bf634f626_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Since fēnix 3 is an activity watch first and foremost, tracking your exercises and adventures, and ability to store an array of data for analysis and statistical purposes, is paramount. Watch comes bundled with a few sport profiles, all of which can be freely, and extensively, customized to your liking. Or deleted to remove clutter, if you so wish. I chose to delete a few and modify the rest to include time as one of the data screen values. I won&rsquo;t walk through all the different settings available, but for example being able to set auto lapping and various alerts (both with vibration notifications of course) and both accent and background color have proved to be useful. As I mentioned, all the settings, also related to Apps, can be modified in the watch, so updating them on the go is very easy. If you find that you are missing, say, an essential data screen from a profile you are using, or for example want to add an alert, you can do that even while recording an exercise. Smart!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157650104285723"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7785/17219705879_115881cf20_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>There is, however, a small caveat when it comes to sport profiles currently. There is only ten (10) available profiles to choose from (Running, Cycling, Pool Swimming, Open Water, Alpine Skiing, XC Ski, Hiking, Mountaineering, Multisport and Other), with seven (7) profile icons, and a generic one, to roughly match these profiles. Being an avid packrafter, I obviously wanted to have a profile for paddle sports, but as you can see, that is not on the default list. I tried the obvious thing, creating a new profile using the Other option, and this was all fine, until I used it for the first time and, returning home, uploaded my data to Garmin Connect. As it turned out, the profile icon I had used, a person with a paddle in his hand, was defining the activity type in Garmin Connect. In this case, stand up paddle boarding was picked, with no evidence of my appropriately named &lsquo;Paddling&rsquo; profile. At first I was sure I had missed something, but a quick check with helpful Garmin support confirmed that profile icon, if chosen, will define the activity type in Garmin Connect, and currently there is no such icon for paddling. What this means is that in case your activities are something other than the nine listed above, you will need to manually update, once uploaded to Garmin Connect, every single exercise, to reflect the correct activity.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157650104285723"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7782/17218130528_e0e0b68b3c_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>A tedious and completely unnecessary task, this is a surprising omission for which I hope there is a change already in the road map. My suggestion would be that  rather than having the profile icon dictating the activity type, why not have a new parameter in the profile configuration, allowing user to choose from the same (25+ excluding sub-activities) list of activities as currently available in Garmin Connect. Profile icons would then only be used for display (as the user pleases), with a shorter, more generic list being sufficient.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157650104285723"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8863/16785648483_66bed06e60_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>In September last year Garmin announced <a href="https://apps.garmin.com/">Connect IQ</a>, allowing third party developers to write applications to run on selected Garmin wearable devices, including fēnix 3. Not limited to creation of new watch faces I already mentioned, this has a huge potential to enhance the user experience both on the watch, as well as on any third party mobile app, that could be interfacing with the watch using this platform, triggering various notifications and exchanging data with a cloud repository. A relatively new platform, the amount of available apps, widgets and for example watch faces is still limited. The rating system in the store (one to five stars and user comments) gives a fair indication of the quality of any given application, but having downloaded quite a few of them, not once have they caused any problems with the watch, so overall quality control seems sufficient. As with any app store, some of the apps are downright silly or appear to be no more than mock-ups, whereas some others are extremely well made, getting the best out of the hardware and the display real estate. Localisations are often omitted, regardless of Garmin allowing access also to localization data with Connect IQ. Downloading any of these apps is made easy by Garmin through the Connect Mobile app on your Apple or Android device: simply flip through them on the phone and download and sync to your watch over bluetooth.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157650104285723"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8692/17218675768_6b18e51426_z.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>I believe the Connect IQ platform has technically everything required for success, if Garmin will ensure it will remain accessible and attractive to developers, for example through easy monetisation of their work, be it creating Apps or Widgets, or introducing smaller enhancements such as Data Fields and Watch Faces, which are the four distinct ways developers can add value here. Monetisation would ensure there will be high quality applications to choose from, which in turn would certainly boost the device sales for Garmin. I for one would not mind paying a small fee from an enhancement I need, similar to smart phones and mobile app stores. Whatever the plans may be, I will be keeping a close eye on the development of this platform, as it can become a true game changer in the wearable domain.</p>

<p>As for the accessories and peripherals, namely the HRM-Run included in the Performance Bundle, there is not much to be said, meaning they complement the fēnix 3 very well. HRM-Run is comfortable to wear, strap being sufficiently wide, and connection to fēnix 3 happens almost instantly, once an activity is started. Same by the way goes also for the GPS lock, being very fast, a lot faster than my Ambit3, taking typically mere seconds. And again, confirmation of the connection and GPS lock can be had as a gentle vibration. I would prefer to be able to change the battery on the heart rate belt without tools, but Garmin has chosen to secure it with 4 small screws instead.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157650104285723"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8795/17219707899_1a92e84d1b_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Sales package includes also USB charger and a kind of miniature docking station for the watch, connecting the device securely over USB, using the four-pin connector on the back of the watch. As with any proprietary connectors, I would prefer they come with detachable cable, to remove unnecessary bulk when securing power and connectivity on the go, across a wide range of electronics. I would however suspect this is not such a common requirement, and hence it is understandable yet another connector (and connection) is omitted, for simplicity and reduced BOM.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157650104285723"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7759/17218131098_30a042a516_z.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Overall I am very pleased with what Garmin has done with their latest iteration of fēnix series watches, packing lot of punch on a stylish, yet robust casing that you willingly strap around your wrist first thing in the morning. Paired with good quality accessories and peripherals, and the fully user configurable Garmin Connect, it leaves a little to be desired. With rather timeless design, and all the current and especially future functional and aesthetical enhancements from Connect IQ should help to keep the device fresh for a long time, and hence also one&rsquo;s update zeal at bay for at least a tiny bit longer.</p>

<p>If you have any questions, post a comment below. I am happy to give more insight on any specific function or feature which you might be intrigued about.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Catalyst Waterproof Case (for iPhone 6)]]></title>
    <link href="http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2015/04/27/Catalyst-Waterproof-Case-iPhone-6/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-27T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2015/04/27/Catalyst-Waterproof-Case-iPhone-6</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My faithful <a href="http://www.ortlieb.de/_prod.php?lang=en&amp;produkt=documentbag">Ortlieb Document Bag</a> starting to disintegrate after years of service, keeping my mobile phones (and a few pocket cameras) dry, it was time to look for a replacement. Offering limited impact protection, I did not consider another waterproof bag, not even the new(ish) <a href="http://www.ortlieb.de/_prod.php?lang=en&amp;produkt=smartphonecase">Smartphone Case</a>, but instead had my eyes on waterproofed hard cases, in which I could securely enclose the iPhone 6.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157651736472497/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7697/16655302304_aecdc47576_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>With plethora of cases to choose from, only a few ticked all the boxes, including the late <a href="http://www.lifeproof.com/shop/us_en/iphone-6-cases/iphone-6-case-nuud/">LifeProof nüüd</a>, soon to be available <a href="https://www.lunatik.com/products/iphone-6/aquatik">Lunatik Aquatik</a>, and the early bird <a href="http://www.catalystlifestyle.com/collections/iphone6/products/iphone-6-black">Catalyst</a>, each of them with slightly different approach to secure one&rsquo;s mobile phone from the elements. With an opportunity given by Catalyst and Vendora Nordic to test and review this case, about a month ago I snapped close the two halves around my phone and here&rsquo;s what I have found out.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157651736472497/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7705/17070327257_4bd0822805_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Catalyst cases have been on the market for quite a while already and the iPhone 6 version was one of the first waterproof cases to hit the market after the launch. You can find some <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fNsnBzToGJk">unboxing videos</a> and user reviews online, some also verifying the shock- and waterproofness, rated (and tested) <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MIL-STD-810">MIL-SPEC 810G</a> for drops and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IP_Code">IP68</a> for waterproofness (liquid and particles actually) by the manufacturer. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WeIhk4ij14w">Some have even put it inside a dish washer</a>, finding no leakages.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157651736472497/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7723/17277254341_edc3e8005a_z.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>During the month I have used the signal orange -detailed <a href="http://www.catalystlifestyle.com/collections/iphone6/products/iphone-6-rescue-ranger">Rescue Ranger</a>, it has gone through a wringer. Used daily to protect my iPhone both in the extreme office environment and in the great outdoors, cycling, hiking and paddling with it, it has proven itself as a trustworthy companion. I have knocked it around, dropped it and gotten it wet repetitively and not once have I had the case failing. Hitting a hard surface case hasn&rsquo;t popped open and the silicone latch on the bottom of the case has proved to be a simple yet very effective way of keeping the insides dry, while allowing easy access to the Lightning and headphone ports. As for compatibility, the headphone port, 6 mm in diameter, should take most of the aftermarket headphones with ease, as long as it comes with a straight jack, including the <a href="http://www.beoplay.com/products/beoplayh3">Beoplay H6&rsquo;s</a> I use daily. For waterproofed connection, or very thick or L-shaped jacks, Catalyst offers an <a href="http://www.catalystlifestyle.com/collections/iphone6/products/catalyst-audio-adapter">Audio Adapter</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649667902074/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7725/16983826779_9f3210a30c_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157651736472497/"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8802/17070327627_4232264325_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>The rubbery outside rim of the case can take a lot of abuse, showing so far no signs of use. The transparent front and back however do have some abrasions in them, though not really noticeable in normal use, except for one recent streak across the front screen.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157651736472497/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7667/16657518483_a798f6ea97_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>I stuff the case carelessly into the <a href="http://leftbound.com/gear/Revelate-Designs-Bikepacking-Gear">frame bag</a>, backpacks and pockets with tools, keys and whatnot already in them, and typically shove it on whatever surface is at hand. Therefore for me superficial scuffs are expected, just proving the case is worth having.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157651736472497/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7685/17277743215_4a8894a3ce_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>I have been taking out phone from the case regularly, to inspect possible structural failures and wear and tear as part of testing, and have found the locking mechanism of the two halves to be robust enough for repetitive assembly and disassemply, always snapping close securely. Volume and lock buttons are snug and require a bit of force to actuate, while still comfortable to use, and the rotating crown dial is an ingenious solution to operate the mute switch on the iPhone. Only if it would come with a small marking to indicate the current position of the dial - phone is muted by turning clockwise/down.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157651736472497/"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8783/16655302164_7512890b16_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157651736472497/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7722/17275955152_3b42cb3191_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157651736472497/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7667/17277254181_0fae0ae4de_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>As a heavy user of Touch ID, not only because of the great <a href="https://agilebits.com/onepassword">1Password</a> app, being able to use it even with a case is a necessity. With Catalyst, the home button is covered with a soft membrane that allows fingerprint biometric scan, which I have found to be working perfectly. You might notice a small bump in this membrane in the pictures, and that is because while unboxing the case with my daughter (who would now very much like to have the <a href="http://www.catalystlifestyle.com/collections/iphone6/products/iphone-6-green-pop">Green Pop</a> version for her 4S), she curiously pressed her finger into the membrane asking what it was - and the membrane, not failing, stretched out a bit. Hardly a defect, it neither has any impact whatsoever to the function of the membrane and the Touch ID, as explained above.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157651736472497/"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8740/16657518653_c0a8c36104_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>For my typical photo- and videography with iPhone, the case performs flawlessly, hard coated lens having no noticeable impact on the picture quality. This is with few inevitable scuffs on the lens, as it is not recessed on the back of the case. Pixel peeping you might see a slight shift in softness in the images, but you would be hard pressed to notice it in normal circumstances.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157651736472497/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7657/17089978808_7f55771f40_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Any phone case, regardless of the level of protection it provides, needs to function without interfering with the usability of the phone. Mechanics aside, Catalyst fares well also in regards to sound quality, as the membranes covering the speakers and the microphone do a great job in passing the sound through. Not once have I had to raise my voice or someone on the line complaining about my voice being muffled, something that has apparently being plaguing for example the new LifeProof nüüd.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157651736472497/"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8802/17277742895_c1dc8d18b0_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Having sunk some electronics in the past, for example one GoPro due to sudden failure of a GorillaPod, I&rsquo;ve learned waterproofness means nothing if you can&rsquo;t retrieve the device from the bottom of the river. Hence I also opted for the <a href="http://www.catalystlifestyle.com/collections/iphone6/products/catalyst-floating-lanyard">Floating Lanyard</a> that I hoped to keep my phone from ending on that sunk-in-action list. A simple, easy to connect accessory, it has enough buoyancy to keep anything up to 250 grams heavy afloat, and comes with a slider to secure it around your wrist if needed. I typically place the phone on the packraft deck, locked down from the lanyard with a carabiner. I would have liked Catalyst to use some sort of brightly colored fabric instead of black that all too easily blends into the murky waters, especially in the dark. Opening the packrafting season a week ago on a nearby flooding river, paddling towards the sunset, I sewed a strip of reflective fabric on it, to be able to spot it easier (with or without a headlamp) against a dark background, if dropped. While all-black is aesthetically a better choice, adding some color would be a reasonable trade-off for improved visibility.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157651736472497/"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8766/17277742875_9c47f06cc7_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157651736472497/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7683/17090220240_7afbb15165_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Based on my experience with the case, I can highly recommend it as a lightweight and low bulk, yet robust protection for your phone, keeping it safe from the elements on your adventures. Several color schemes to choose from and a range of add-on accessories and spare parts should cover all your needs and preferences. Purchase the case directly from <a href="http://www.catalystlifestyle.com">catalystlifestyle.com</a>, or if you reside in Europe, I can also recommend <a href="http://www.lifestylestore.se/">lifestylestore.se</a>, with flat rate shipping for 9.99 EUR only, within EU.</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: At the time of reviewing this product, I had no affiliation with Catalyst, and receiving the product free of charge for testing had no influence on the content, or my opinions about this particular product. In May 2015, I became an ambassador for Catalyst.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Xiaomi Mi Power Bank]]></title>
    <link href="http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2015/04/17/Xiaomi-Mi-Power-Bank/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-17T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2015/04/17/Xiaomi-Mi-Power-Bank</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There is obviously plenty of electronics manufactured in and exported from China, lots of it being counterfeit copies of branded products. Usually functioning, but often lacking some of the features and typically made of inferior materials with no proper quality control, they are easily obtained from various online stores and through eBay. The product I am about to discuss, also made in China, is however a legit one - The <a href="http://www.mi.com/sg/mipowerbank/">Mi Power Bank</a> by Xiaomi. This statement comes with a twist of irony though, as the company behind it is, with its founder and CEO Lei Jun, known for <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2014/07/30/xiaomis-one-more-thing/">blatantly ripping off especially Apple</a>, all the way down to the mannerisms of late Steve Jobs. A young, hungry company aiming to the global markets, they are not one to be ignored, but I will leave it here, and instead dive into the product itself, which is actually very good.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649667902074/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7648/17144071226_810ce8b4f0_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Looking for reasonable means to ensure my battery-operated cadgets have power when I need it, I was quickly drawn into different types of power banks. Small and simple to use, yet robust enough to throw around, I have for a long time already used a couple of <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Nokia-Universal-Connection-Compatible-Smartphones-Black/dp/B007VN3E4I">Nokia DC-16&rsquo;s</a>, a 2200 mAh portable power bank capable of recharging for example a typical smart phone once. A narrow cylinder weighting just shy of 80 grams, they are handy to carry around just in case.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649667902074/"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8701/16962589367_fbaa45a14c_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Wanting more capacity, enough to keep several devices running for extended time, I researched the available products and quickly ended up ordering a 10400 mAh <a href="http://www.dx.com/p/xiaomi-10400mah-usb-mobile-power-source-bank-w-4-led-indicators-silver-white-311565#.VTAD41zGBE4">Xiaomi Mi Power Bank from DealExtreme</a>. Ironically again, also Xiaomi suffers from counterfeiting, and copies of their power banks are widely sold for example in eBay. If you decide to order one, try to ensure you get the real deal. If in doubt, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=obYhTgzEVP8">check this video</a> to get a confirmation. In my opinion the two crucial things are the incomplete circuitry and the no-name cells typically found in the fake ones. Real one uses LG, Samsung and other branded cells, with full specified capacity.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649667902074/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7725/16983826779_9f3210a30c_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>The unit is made of plastic and aluminum, with a simple interface of micro USB and USB ports, with indicator leds and a reset button. Connecting a device automatically turns on the charging circuitry and once disconnected, the unit powers off automatically so you don&rsquo;t accidentally drain the unit. There is also short circuit protection, and unit has enough ampage to charge most of the portable devices, including an iPad. I have tossed it around quite carelessly (though often storing it in a cutout pockect, saved from an old disintegrated pair of merino wool pants) and dropped it few times, with only some odd scratches on the aluminum casing. The unit weighs 255 grams without cables.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649667902074/"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8791/16983826189_a371372e61_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>I have used this power bank now for almost a year, with absolutely no issues. Circuitry works reliably (it is essentially plug and play with little interaction needed), and the 10400 mAh capacity has proved to be just the right amount for most of my needs, while still keeping the bulk at minimum. Xiaomi has also 5000 mAh and 16000 mAh version of this power bank, both of which share the same looks, with a slightly different shape and size. I have used mine to charge my iPhone and iPad of course, but also my wristop computers and <a href="http://www.petzl.com/en/Sport/PERFORMANCE-headlamps/NAO">Petzl Nao</a> head lamp. Recently purchased <a href="https://buy.garmin.com/en-GB/GB/outdoor/handheld/etrex-20/prod87771.html">Garmin eTrex 20</a> and <a href="http://store.sony.com/cyber-shot-digital-camera-rx100-iii-zid27-DSCRX100M3/B/cat-ProductChannelAssignments-catid-SNYUSAssignments">Sony RX100 III</a> can also be topped up with this power bank, essentially leaving no gaps when it comes to electronics I might have with me when heading out. As the unit only comes with a micro USB - USB cable adapters are necessary, but getting one of those micro USB to anything adapter kits sorts it out. Unfortunately though both Suunto and Garmin wristop computers use proprietary connectors and hence add unnecessary bulk to the kit. On the other hand Nao requires no cables at all, as the removable battery has a male USB.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649667902074/"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8797/16982243028_c0b7407e7a_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649667902074/"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8811/16549832823_6ff205427a_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649667902074/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7650/16547581174_5a296aa339_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649667902074/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7603/16549833353_9cf6889ae3_z.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649667902074/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7655/16982468090_3d2ce37df0_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>In case you are on the lookout for a mobile power source, but not ready to invest into <a href="http://www.brunton.com/products/hydrogen-reactor-plus-hydrogen-core">hydrogen reactors</a> or <a href="http://www.brunton.com/collections/solar">solar power</a>, the Mi Power Bank is worth considering. It even comes in multiple bright colors, if the basic white and silver theme does not cut it for you.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649667902074/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7643/17169386641_05232bee58_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
