<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Hiking | Leftbound]]></title>
  <link href="http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/categories/hiking/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://leftbound.com/leftbound/"/>
  <updated>2018-01-25T00:41:20+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://leftbound.com/leftbound/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Joni Palomäki]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[joni@leftbound.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bogged Out at Tremanskärr]]></title>
    <link href="http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2016/10/10/Bogged-Out-At-Tremanskarr/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-10T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2016/10/10/Bogged-Out-At-Tremanskarr</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It was over ten years ago, when I was considering moving to <a href="https://www.google.fi/maps/place/Kalaj%C3%A4rvi,+02970+Espoo/@60.3013464,24.7191791,13.34z/data=!4m5!3m4!1s0x468df0950f191c09:0xa00b553b98df620!8m2!3d60.3046552!4d24.7372842">Kalajärvi</a>, right at the border of Espoo and Vantaa in the north. While on a lookout for an apartment there, checking the area out, I noticed there is also a small bog not far away, north of Kalajärvi. As plans changed and I ended up on the other side of Espoo, I never did go to that area in particular and only now, on an autumn day, cranberries ripening, decided to finally visit this forgotten pearl.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/30158487211/in/album-72157673753325311/" title="Duckboards"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/6/5807/30158487211_ba267ee7af_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Duckboards"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The <a href="http://www.espoo.fi/fi-FI/Tremanskarr__Espoon_suoluonnon_helmi">nature reserve</a>, that gets its name from the large bog, Tremanskärr, was established in 1986. Not very large in size, only around 45 hectares, there are nature trails that circulate the area, and following the well-marked, figure-eight-shaped route, one gets a complete tour across the reserve.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/29614380993/in/photostream/" title="Nature trail"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5454/29614380993_39bb9fba18_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Nature trail"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The main bog is rather special in southern Finland, due to the way it&rsquo;s been formed. Rather than being the typical overgrown lake or a pond, Tremanskär was born at the aftermath of a forest fire. Without trees to absorb excess moisture from the soil, and ground water rising, previously forested land gradually transformed into peatland some 3000 years ago.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/30244125305/in/album-72157673753325311/" title="Duckboards"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5539/30244125305_a7e9aeb669_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Duckboards"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Tremanskär drains northwest into Kurkijärvi, a grand but shallow forest pond. Large aspen trees, rugged wilderness valleys and morasses cut across the woodland.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/29947505530/in/album-72157673753325311/" title="Kurkijärvi"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/9/8720/29947505530_a254400d47_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Kurkijärvi"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/30209304736/in/photostream/" title="Trail"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8419/30209304736_58aa6b2823_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Trail"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I hoped to find some ripe cranberries, though it was still relatively early in the season, and did find plenty, hiding in the underbrush. No cloudberries were seen, but plenty of overripe and bland bilberries still hung heavy on the branched stems.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/29614371413/in/album-72157673753325311/" title="Cranberries"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/6/5649/29614371413_3db7cbf5ba_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Cranberries"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/30209301776/in/album-72157673753325311/" title="Bilberries"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/6/5575/30209301776_7e758449d4_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Bilberries"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Aside of duckboards and few wooden benches, there are no fixed structures nor fire places in the area. Trails were all clean with no trash at sight, even though the area is easily accessible from a parking lot - not sure how much traffic there is though. Signboards scattered along trails present useful bite-sized info about the history and wildlife of the area.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/29613588104/in/album-72157673753325311/" title="Duckboards"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/6/5677/29613588104_f409761cbb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Duckboards"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>&#10095;&#10095; Flickr album (with more photos): <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/albums/72157673753325311">Bogged out at Tremanskärr</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Iceland Revisited]]></title>
    <link href="http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2015/07/13/Iceland-Revisited/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-13T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2015/07/13/Iceland-Revisited</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Since I <a href="http://leftbound.com/blog/2013/06/07/Scratching-Iceland/">visited Iceland for the first time</a>, back in 2013, for work, I promised myself I would be back soonest, in this particularly stunning piece of land in the middle of the North Atlantic. Come this spring, I saw an opportunity to have a go at the classic <a href="http://www.landmannalaugar.info/">Landmannalaugar</a> trail, and drafted a rough plan to cover the trail over a long weekend in June. As this hike, during the peak season also playfully referred to as Laugavegur trail (after the busy main street of Reykjavik) trail, meets a lot of traffic during the summer months, once all the huts and backcountry roads are open, I scheduled my flights as early as possible in June, trying to avoid the worst crowd.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157655773373116"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3681/19047524374_131d331055_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>While the plan overall appeared solid, I hadn&rsquo;t accounted for the very late summer in Scandinavia this year, that turned out to be, in Iceland, unlike any since 1969. Summer arriving late, it meant the highland roads were blocked by snow, making it impossible even for the super jeeps to travel, keeping huts on the northern end of the trails shut, obviously blocking also the buses transporting hikers to the area. Another small surprise upon landing was finding all my spare batteries been confiscated by the airport security at Helsinki, leaving me with only one battery inside the camera. Luckily I had the <a href="http://leftbound.com/blog/2015/04/17/Xiaomi-Mi-Power-Bank/">Xiaomi Power Bank</a> with me, so I did not miss them in the end, charging the one I had directly inside the Sony RX100 III.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157655773373116"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/367/19674577021_f4a3c3b07e_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157655773373116"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3780/19643896616_806f52053d_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Having only booked the flight and the airport transport with <a href="https://www.re.is/flybus/">Flybus</a> to <a href="http://www.reykjavikcampsite.is/">Reykjavik Campsite</a>, not tying myself into a fixed schedule, upon arrival I was met with news about Landmannalaugar still being buried in snow, making my original plan futile. I unloaded all the gear into my Tarptent Rainbow pitched in the grassy field among a melange of shelters, jumped to a bus 14, and headed downtown. Seated in the great <a href="http://www.fishandchips.is/">Icelandic Fish &amp; Chips</a> restaurant, quadrupled in size since my last visit, I locked down to the free wifi over some local beer and delicious catch of the day, and started pondering over my options for the next four days. Before the dinner was done, I had decided to head to Skógar instead, and start hiking towards north, leaving the finish open as the conditions on the trail in the next few days, and the storm just about to hit the south coast, would allow.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157655773373116"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/407/19643896426_240356e62c_z.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>The great thing about traveling in Iceland, in addition to very affordable direct flights from Helsinki to Keflavik, is the comprehensive network of buses running around the island, and into the selected huts and trail ends, and of course to plethora of attractions. For hikers, both <a href="https://www.re.is/">Reykjavik Excursions</a> and <a href="http://trex.is/">Trex</a> are companies to get in touch with. I opted for the <a href="http://trex.is/hikers-bus-pass2/">Hiker&rsquo;s Bus Pass</a> from Trex, which is essentially an open return ticket to selected stops, guaranteeing a seat without committing to a specific date. There are few passes to choose from, and as I planned to start from Skógar, I purchased one covering Skógar, Þórsmörk and Landmannalaugar. Hence, starting from Skógar, I would have the option to retreat from Þórsmörk, once over the mountains and through the Fimmvörðuháls pass, or to continue up to my original starting point at Landmannalaugar, should the hut and hence the bus connection be opened by the time I could, possibly, reach that high point.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157655773373116"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3803/19047523524_0123caafa6_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>With an early awakening, I jumped to the bus at the campsite (another perk for staying there, no transfer to BSÍ bus station required) and by 10:30 arrived to the Skógafoss waterfall, majestically marking the trail end with a 60-meter drop over a former coastline cliff. I had visited this place in 2013 on my day-tour along the south coast, and with storm rising on the sea behind my back, and heavy precipitation forecasted later the day in the mountains ahead of me, I skipped the attraction and hit the stairs going up next to the waterfall, hoping to gain ground and escape at least some of the bad weather. The hike up along Skógá River towards the Fimmvörðuháls pass is spotted with views into the mountains ahead and the river on your left, running through deep gorges and over multitude of waterfalls, with a roar. Gaining elevation, wind from northeast became stronger and gusty and meeting some other hikers taking shelter behind a boulder about half-way up the mountain learned about 15-18 m/s readings from their carry-on anemometer. And then the wind picked up.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157655773373116"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3793/19674576701_9570ba9d49_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>I had met two chaps from UK at the trail end, arriving in the same bus, and as we turned out to have the same brisk pace, I ended up having some good company and outdoorsy chat on the way up, fighting the wind. Catching up few hikers, there was some oncoming traffic, including a group that had turned around in the snowline, where a bridge crosses the river. As the group was somewhat ill-prepared, with at least one of the guys missing his gloves, that was probably a smart move, as the conditions continued to get worse.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157655773373116"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/484/19047523344_432fbc5947_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Stopping behind a crop of rocks for a quick lunch, our group of three was met with a sight of a person hiking up behind us with a bike on his shoulder. As I later learned, it was some misinformation from a bike shop in Reykjavik that had encouraged this tough cyclist to hit the trail and try to cycle through the Fimmvörðuháls pass in one go, some 25 km in total distance. Perfectly doable in normal summer conditions, it turned out to be an epic hike-a-bike, as he joined our loose group and pushed all the way up to the manned hut some 2 km before the pass, where we stopped over for shelter, and ended up spending the night there, as the weather continued to deteriorate. We were later joined by more solo hikers and groups and ended up having a full house before the night fell.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157655773373116"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/484/19047523294_f8a44ef799_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157655773373116"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3829/19047523274_ef22c1de72_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157655773373116"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/501/19047523234_be5fa7d572_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Listening to the rumble of wind shaking the hut through the night, morning brought significantly better conditions, while wind remained relatively strong throughout the day. Visibility had improved, and even sun was peeking between the rolling clouds, so it was time to pack up and hit the trail again. I bid farewell to my earlier companions, and continued up in the mountain in solitude. Reaching the pass, weather kept on improving and I was strolling between the two glaciers and past Magni and Móði, the two new volcanoes formed when Eyjafjallajokull erupted in 2010. Soil around them is still warm to touch.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157655773373116"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/516/19482066438_4c8ba0ef8c_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157655773373116"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3733/19049165133_1c71c0f52a_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157655773373116"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3725/19674576381_4156d3b63a_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Before heading down the other side, one must pass a ridge that proved to be an interesting alpine-style scramble, with gusty wind trying to knock you over the edge. On the lower plateau, with a steep snow slope to tackle at first, I reached the snowline and with a pretty traverse over a mountain side I was back on the green, in the lush meadows with glaciated mountains as the backdrop.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157655773373116"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3721/19663005502_a0bcd707ef_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157655773373116"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3752/19643895746_57dc5c317e_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157655773373116"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3752/19663005302_1647b30a3c_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Down in the valley, in Þórsmörk, I took a short break, filled up the water bottles, and then decided to continue on the trail, heading north towards Botnar, some 19 kilometers away. With dark clouds approaching from the east, I decided I would hiked for few kilometers and camp somewhere nice along the trail.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157655773373116"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/486/19047522704_d97784f89e_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157655773373116"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3700/19482065908_2bb07c3145_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157655773373116"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/287/19482110860_4a94084a48_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Couple of kilometers in I arrived to the first river crossing. I had brought a pair of lightweight Salomon running shoes for camp shoes and for crossing rivers, and though already proven over the previous day of pushing into the wind, I had brought the collapsible hiking poles, Distance Carbon FLZ from Black Diamond, especially to secure the river crossings while traveling alone. Crossing turned out to be an easy one, water running only at a knee high on a wider spot I chose, and the ones further down the trail were possible to cross with dry feet - I wore <a href="http://www.lasportiva.com/en/mountaineering/mountaineering-man/mens/details/products/trango-guide-evo-gore-tex/">La Sportiva Trango Guide Evo&rsquo;s</a> on this trip - these comfortable and lightweight mountain boots provided good support on the mixed terrain.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157655773373116"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/311/19674577581_3ab540630c_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157655773373116"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/545/19674577411_aa29efc3d1_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Few kilometers onwards the terrain shifted and became more barren, and choosing an alternative trail instead of the Landmannalaugar trail with blue route markers, I made way through the erored Almenningar pastures and feeling fresh I decided I would continue all the way to Botnar in one go. Weather got gradually grimmer, wind as a constant companion, and even some rain fell towards the end of the trail. Once I reached the Botnar hut, I had hiked around 32 kilometers in about 10 hours (of which 7 hours moving), with some 1000 meters of ascent, and 1400 meters descent, according to the Garmin fēnix3 statistics. It was time to pitch up the tent in a windy plateau, supported with piles of rocks and extra guylines. Despite the wind pounding and binding on it, it held up fine. Talking to the hut warden I learned my wishful plan to get a lift out from the next hut at Álftavatn was futile, as despite the hut already being opened, no transportation would run to and from it at least for a week. At the same time there was a strong rumor that the Landmannalaugar hut (and the bus connection to and from Reykjavik) would be opened the next day. Rehydrating and loading up on calories I pondered whether I should continue to Álftavatn the next day, and try to get to Landmannalaugar (presuming it was to be open) in one push from there (some 25 kilometers over the snow covered mountains), or would I be better off returning to Þórsmörk instead and spending the remaining day off this trail.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157655773373116"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/443/19482065538_b8e4931f26_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157655773373116"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/277/19670097185_b9efbf2416_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157655773373116"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/490/19643895126_7c2650211a_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157655773373116"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/326/19670097045_c0ca18c16a_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157655773373116"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3699/19047522094_32e225e637_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>With the unknowns regarding Landmannalaugar transportation and and conditions up in the mountains ahead, I decided the next morning I would head back to Þórsmörk, and give the trail another go at another time, when I would not need to rush it through bad weather, while risking missing my flight back home. Hardly disappointed, I enjoyed finally some tailwind while hiking back to Þórsmörk, now following the blue Landmannalaugar signposts through slightly more green pastures. Dark clouds rolled around me, hiking essentially in the eye of the small storm around in the mountains and the coastal sea, while I made it back to Þórsmörk well on time for the bus transport back to Reykjavik.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157655773373116"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3776/19675215971_0136482e3d_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157655773373116"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/402/19670740365_7467574ed8_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157655773373116"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/455/19484102439_a9115c16fa_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157655773373116"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3698/19644530306_0919f8f0ce_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Back in the town, and in the Campsite, I got a confirmation that indeed the Landmannalaugar hut had been opened that day, and buses were running according to the normal summer schedules. For a brief moment I considered jumping into one next morning and making a day trip to the trail end, but quickly decided I would head to another direction. Weather forecast around the Landmannalaugar trail (and in the south coast in general) promised rain and poor visibility, so I decided to leave that behind me and chase the sun up north.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157655773373116"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3797/19049164193_a6b1e79baf_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157655773373116"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/286/19643894886_ca755dcdc5_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Come next morning, I booked a car at the reception, and in half an hour I was picked up to sign it off the at the rental office. With my airport transfer leaving at around 22:00, I decided I would have enough time to explore the Western Region, driving all the way to the small town of Hellissandur, and around the peninsula, following the coastal roads.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157655773373116"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3794/19482065238_604cf10d65_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157655773373116"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3790/19663004152_b6095737f9_z.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>It turned out to be a great day filled with sunshine and warmth, with more spectacular views of Iceland and the North Atlantic, visiting waterfalls and caves, crossing glaciated mountains and watching seals. I hadn&rsquo;t met any Finns during the trip, but finally did, picking up two girls hitchhiking near Hellissandur. We shared a short ride together as I dropped them off at the the Snaefellsjoekull National Park.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157655773373116"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/498/19483464859_c7d0192b83_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157655773373116"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3774/19674575271_cd6ec97123_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157655773373116"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3795/19663003972_77146b9621_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Back in the Campsite, I dropped the car keys in the reception, and met <a href="https://www.etsy.com/shop/pureIceland">Agga</a> who had made me a very fine custom fitted (and designed) <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lopapeysa">Lopapeysa</a> wool sweater. Before heading to the airport, oblivious to the fact my hard shell would be left behind, on the backseat of the rental car, I had a delicious lobster soup at the restaurant next door, the <a href="http://www.laugaas.is/">Lauga-ás</a>. Then it was just the night flight back to Helsinki, followed by a busy day at work.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157655773373116"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/337/19050016253_b461926fc3_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>The question is not whether I will go back, but simply when it will be, though I already got my jacket back on the mail. Obviously Iceland is far from done, and while I am not really bummed about the change of plans and not being able to tackle the whole of Landmannalaugar trail as originally planned, I might be back to do the rest of it. Or, I might as well try to cover again some new areas in this wonderland of fire and ice. I will likely start planning something that would involve a bike and/or a packraft, but for that, if just for the logistics of it, I would need some more time on the ground. However, with relatively cheap direct flights from Helsinki, and the nowadays comprehensive bus network around the island and in and out the trail ends, it certainly is a good destination also for shorter trips, compared to for example northern Sweden and Norway where I&rsquo;ve been going to in the past, having to spend almost two days just for the travel.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157655773373116"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/560/19047522474_2883e263a8_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>In addition to a map and a compass you should naturally bring with you, I can highly recommend <a href="http://www.ourfootprints.de/gps/mapsource-island_e.html">this</a> free MapSource map, that covers most of the known trails (obviously including also the Landmannalaugar) and mountain roads, and is hence a good resource if you carry a compatible GPS device. I have a basic Garmin eTrex 20 that runs on two AA-sized batteries (Alkaline, Lithium or NiMH), small and inexpensive with all the essentials (except USB charging), which I brought along as a backup.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157655773373116"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3731/19482252550_7ff472c879_z.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>While I enjoy traveling alone, it is always great to meet people all around the world on the trail and share some moments together. If you happen to run across this blog, feel free to comment below or <a href="mailto:joni@leftbound.com">drop me an email</a>, I might even have some photos to share.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157655773373116"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/502/19663641702_ee5b018132_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157655773373116">More photos in Flickr</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Nuijapoloku]]></title>
    <link href="http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2015/04/07/Nuijapoloku/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-07T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2015/04/07/Nuijapoloku</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Visiting Ostrobothnia over Easter, despite the typically busy schedule trying to meet everyone, friends and family, I managed to snatch a day for myself. Having found a handy resource <a href="http://leftbound.com/blog/2014/04/23/Suupohja-Sample/">last summer</a>, for <a href="http://www.seikkailesuupohjassa.fi/en">outdoor destinations in the Suupohja region</a>, I had already earmarked few potential destinations for a day out, and decided to head towards Kurikka this time, visiting one of the &lsquo;mountains&rsquo; of Ostrobothnia, <a href="http://www.suupohjankehittamisyhdistys.fi/site?node_id=559&amp;action=show_data&amp;p_id=119&amp;ordercol=p_id&amp;ordertype=desc&amp;row=3">Santavuori</a> (merely a hill of course) and the trails around it, named as <a href="http://www.suupohjankehittamisyhdistys.fi/site?node_id=559&amp;action=show_data&amp;p_id=92&amp;ordercol=p_id&amp;ordertype=desc&amp;row=12">Nuijapoloku</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157651401920098/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7644/17038841956_79336a65dc_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->


<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157651401920098/"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8710/16877029928_02c8a43d19_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157651401920098/"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8754/16442380534_0d7cc610b3_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Nuijapoloku is a tribute to the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cudgel_War">Cudgel War</a>, &lsquo;Nuijasota&rsquo;, a peasant upprising against nobles and infrantry back in 1596 (when the country was still a kingdom of Sweden), a fight for freedom and justice. Name refers to the rudimentary weapons used against the professional troops of Clas Eriksson Fleming. Despite some initial success, the rebellion was in the end forcefully suppressed - the final battle took place in Santavuori, demanding lives of over thousand insurgents.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157651401920098/"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8696/16877030188_f42513fbe5_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Arriving to the <a href="https://www.google.com/maps/place/62%C2%B038'41.8%22N+22%C2%B027'21.4%22E/@62.6449431,22.455956,17z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m2!3m1!1s0x0:0x0">parking place</a>, I started to follow the rather well marked trail towards Santavuori. There are four different trails to choose from, ranging from 5 to 21 kilometers in length (from blue to white) - I decided to follow the yellow trail, which was the longest round-trip, not having to hike the same trails twice.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157651401920098/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7619/16444670763_c791204693_z.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Trail was mostly well marked, but at times I had to search for the correct way since some of the sign posts were either lost, or the route was intersected with recent clear cuts, some of which were due to 16 wind turbines that will be erected in Santavuori by end of 2016.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157651401920098/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7658/16878598629_0184ace7bb_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157651401920098/"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8690/16878598869_a82e64923a_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>There were several spots to stop for a lunch and a sleepover, be it a laavu or a hut with a fireplace inside. I visited every one of them, and had a lunch by the fire in Leevinkota, a closed teepee-styled hut roughly half-way of the yellow trail. Always nice to eat something local, I had stopped at Ilmajoki on the way, and had a package of tasty blue cheese sausages by <a href="http://www.makkaramestarit.fi">Ilmajoen Makkaramestarit</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157651401920098/"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8818/16857423237_76e897a4b0_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>I met no other people the whole day, and while I could see some footprints close to the parking lot at the starting point, further down the partly snowy trails I saw no sign of visitors. Guestbooks in the huts had most recent entries from couple of week&rsquo;s back.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157651401920098/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7605/16877281410_b002864cb0_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157651401920098/"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8699/17064827145_cc591eedfb_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>With little traffic, I hoped to get a glimpse of some wildlife and treading lightly kept my eyes open. Bears and wolves are not uncommon, but other than few types of fowls, including the very common pheasants and a large owl (could have been an eagle owl), larger animals managed not to cross my path. Regardless, it was an nice day out, and was happy to have a chance to visit the trail and the area before the imminent changes by the wind farming.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157651401920098/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7677/16444671523_e82b55f939_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157651401920098/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7587/17064045711_fc8a99f3e4_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>While certainly a nice place for the locals to hike in, the clear cuts and stretches of trail following the forest roads, and sections across the farm fields, make it less attractive for someone not living closer by (or being in the area for other reasons, such as myself). Good thing is that not far away there are also other spots to visit, and that <a href="http://www.suupohjankehittamisyhdistys.fi/site?node_id=575">Suupohja online resource</a> makes it easy to map down and connect some of the different destinations if heading to that general direction.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157651401920098/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7647/16442381034_be9132599d_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157651401920098/"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8748/16857423087_f4f83ddd86_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157651401920098/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7725/16442380824_baa5991539_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157651401920098/">Few more photos in Flickr</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Suupohja Sample]]></title>
    <link href="http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2014/04/23/Suupohja-Sample/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-23T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2014/04/23/Suupohja-Sample</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Heading to Ostrobothnia around Easter for family festive, I planned to take some time on my own and visit some of the interesting outdoor spots nearby. While searching, I ran across <a href="http://www.suupohjankehittamisyhdistys.fi">Suupohja Development Association</a> (Suupohjan Kehittämisyhdistys ry), and their <a href="http://www.seikkailesuupohjassa.fi/en">extremely usefull resource</a>, especially for a casual visitor like myself, for locating the best destinations in the Suupohja region. Not only is it well made (with introductions in nine languages altogether, though the site itself is in Finnish only) and easy to use, but each destination is described in sufficient detail, and completed with photos, precise coordinates and a map link. With these details, I was able to quickly choose interesting spots in a specific area, and had a plan ready before I left Espoo.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157644232081974/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7159/13975597194_670e6c8817_o.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>To capitalize the hours available but still wanting to visit more than one place, I chose three different destinations relatively close to each other, and headed out at dawn, maxing out with roughly 8 hours on the go.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157644232081974/"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2896/13971976291_e092417576_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Starting from Isokyrö, my first destination was a <a href="http://www.suupohjankehittamisyhdistys.fi/site?node_id=557&amp;action=show_data&amp;p_id=89&amp;ordercol=p_id&amp;ordertype=desc&amp;row=13">lookout tower and a hut on Myötämäenkallio</a>, close to <a href="http://fi.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jurva">Jurva</a> (merged with <a href="http://www.kurikka.fi/?lang=en">Kurikka</a> back in 2007). I parked the car at the link mast as suggested, and following the trail and random sign posts it was a short hike to the tower, suddenly rising up behind the trees. The tower is actually an old fire tower, bought and moved on the site by the Tainuskylä village society in 2006.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157644232081974/"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5474/13971956002_ba33a52f83_o.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Climbing the ladders, through a hatch and into the small wooden box to the top of the all steel structure 144,5 meters over the sea level offers an open view all around and to a distance, as far as my northbound destination of the day, Levaneva bog. It was a windy day, so I swayed away for a short moment for a few photos before heading back down to check the hut nearby.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157644232081974/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7021/13975596284_f4d9ae905c_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Just behind the tower there&rsquo;s luxurious hut, fully maintained with an outhouse and firewood supply. Based on the logbook entries it seemed to have a steady flow of visitors and with a good supply of billberries and funnel chantarelles at the right time of the year, it certainly is a nice spot for day trips and family outings.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157644232081974/"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5188/13975597044_9a39ba0ccd_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Back in the car I took a bearing towards <a href="http://www.suupohjankehittamisyhdistys.fi/site?node_id=557&amp;action=show_data&amp;p_id=91&amp;ordercol=p_id&amp;ordertype=desc&amp;row=11">Niinistönjärvi</a> lake. A bog lake of decent size, trails run around it, with a bird-watching tower and a few fire places. I spotted a pair of Common Cranes nearby the tower, and sadly all too many seagulls, populating the lake. <a href="http://www.reinontupa.fi/en/startpage">Reinon Tupa</a> has facilities around the lake, and they organize activities especially for groups, with full service.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157644232081974/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7101/13995146333_8247e34f31_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157644232081974/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7149/13971956682_8417b2062b_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>After a short stop and hike in the surroundings of Niinistönjärvi it was time to head to the main destination, <a href="http://www.suupohjankehittamisyhdistys.fi/site?node_id=557&amp;action=show_data&amp;p_id=88&amp;ordercol=p_id&amp;ordertype=desc&amp;row=14">Kurjenkierros trail</a>, and specifically to Kivi- ja Levalampi reservoir and Levaneva bog on the border of Jurva and Laihia. I wanted to do a round trip, and as the Kurjenkierros trail itself runs from point to point, almost 50 kilometers in length, I packed the packraft with me, to first hike on the trail and across the bog, and then paddle back along the reservoir.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157644232081974/"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2908/13952055356_ccb01ed67f_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157644232081974/"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5166/13975151785_8030104141_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.luontoon.fi/retkikohteet/muutsuojelualueet/levaneva/Sivut/Default.aspx">Levaneva</a> is a vast, several kilometers wide raised bog, extending as far as the eye can see - it&rsquo;s actually the largest mire reserve across Ostrobothnia, well preserved due to its size and location. Trail fully equipped with duckboards and blue dots as route markers when on dry land, it&rsquo;s an easy stride with spectacular views.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157644232081974/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7273/13971977221_79e4ca2788_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157644232081974/"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5019/13975154685_8b437eb981_o.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157644232081974/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7020/13971957752_27c66289b4_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157644232081974/"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2904/13952056176_1cb459a8eb_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157644232081974/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7437/13975154925_f90a680a33_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157644232081974/"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5190/13975598834_dabd8b89d2_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157644232081974/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7190/13995148013_5834f395c7_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157644232081974/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7137/13952056266_e93ba3e237_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157644232081974/"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2898/13971978141_e259d81109_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Reaching a suitable spot to try and enter the reservoir, I inflated the packraft and begun a semi-wet entry procedure that consisted of route finding while hopping from tuft to tuft, hoping not to sink more than a knee deep to the depths of ice cold and murky waters of the wetland, bordering the reservoir on the northeast corner.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157644232081974/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7192/13975599264_eeb0220b6d_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157644232081974/"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2927/13975599054_da2fe269a6_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157644232081974/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7169/13975599074_6019e548c1_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>While entering the raft, and quickly slipping my chilled feet into Sealskins, I noticed the strong wind that had picked up by the hour was directly against me, and so I started the persistent fight against it, not made any easier by the increasing swell and small whitecapped waves. Distance of just a couple of kilometers took some effort to conquer, though part of me (the part that was not concerned about me missing my sister&rsquo;s wedding) was enjoying the struggle.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157644232081974/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7157/13975155955_b8ecb50bf9_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>I finished the round trip with a smile on my face, close the Maalarinmaa bird-watching tower from where I had started, in the nick of time. Great day overall, and definitely left an itch to explore the Suupohja region more once the summer arrives (perhaps some kind of a bikepacking tour in July, when I will most likely be in the area next time).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Enter Winter]]></title>
    <link href="http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2012/12/03/Enter-Winter/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-03T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2012/12/03/Enter-Winter</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Winter has been making its flamboyant entrance in the capital area for the last few days, creating some trouble again in Helsinki downtown, and on the roads and sea, with snow being blown all around in the high wind, and eventually covering everything under a calming white blanket, tens of centimeters thick.</p>

<p>These long awaited scenic changes, followed by a temperature drop towards the weekend, put a night out on the menu to get the winter activities kickstarted, and together with Mikko and Karsten, we headed out for an overnighter in Nuuksio national park on Saturday. Entering Nuuksio, and heading towards Holma-Saarijärvi lean-to to spend an evening around the campfire, views were not quite like just a week ago when I was hiking with my daughter in the same surroundings:</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157641626224314/"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7402/12800787865_88a5f455de_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Heading out from Siikajärvi after eight in the evening, breaking trail, headlights were hardly needed under the ambient light diffused from the early descending moon. Duckboards were still evil, hiding under the snow and inviting a twisted ankle - same hide and seek went on with muddy potholes not quite frozen solid yet. We crossed some fresh footprints on the way but luckily didn&rsquo;t see anyone, and we had the lean-to at Holma-Saarijärvi all to ourselves - we didn&rsquo;t bring a tent but shovels and a plan to dig ourselves in the snow if needed.</p>

<p>Arriving to the camp the temperature was around -10 °C (based on a keyring thermometer), so quite pleasant still for hanging around in the camp. Cleaning up after previous visitors and chopping some fresh firewood we toasted to winter with some <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gammel_Dansk">Gammel Dansk Bitter Dram</a>, and had a festive dinner (sausages of course) with the usual around the fire discussions on anything and everything, and strolling around the camp and gazing the clearing sky spotted by stars.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157641626224314/"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7307/12800888953_1620a5a132_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157641626224314/"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3790/12801210094_b287518fbc_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Karsten could not stay overnight, so we had plenty of space with Mikko in the 4-person lean-to. Forecast had promised the temperature should drop down to around -15 °C during the night, and the clearing sky suggested the same shift in temperature. Tucked in our sleeping bags later at night we call it the day, to wake up to a bright morning some 8 hours later. I usually sleep well in the outdoors and this night was no different, although I did slide off the slippery NeoAir (stacked on top of a thick Karrimat I use in the winter) few times and woke up when cold started to creep in on the lean-to floor) - quick look on the keyring testified the temperature had indeed dropped a bit, down to around -16 °C in the wee hours of the night.</p>

<p>In the morning I stayed in the camp while Mikko rushed off for family errands, and prepared some delicious (not really) Trek'n Eat vanilla rice pudding by the fire, followed by some minty hot chocolate, while light snow started to fall again.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157641626224314/"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2865/12801209754_83dbedfc7f_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157641626224314/"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7405/12801209604_9a124c2d24_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Packing up and cleaning the campsite, I hiked down to Haukkalampi, and back around towards Siikajärvi where I had my car parked, breaking trail and taking photos mostly in solitude (crisscrossing around 8 kilometers I met only 3 other hikers). I brought the newly acquired Olympus E-M5 with me, paired with Yashica ML 50 f1.9 (an old solid mechanical lens from past decades which I bought a year ago when trying out the E-PM1) - all the photos shown here were shot with this combo. E-M5 is weather sealed and I did not worry much about the lens either, just kept brushing off the snow while the kit hung from my neck or around the shoulder, ready to shoot.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157641626224314/"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3800/12800888643_630e9ca0ff_o.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>On this trip I was also looking forward to try out a new pair of winter gloves I found half the price during the summer on a closeout sale of Camu store in Tampere - Rab Latok. Until then I had been looking to find a winter-spec&rsquo;d version of something not quite unlike Marmot XT gloves (which I&rsquo;ve grown fond of while alpine climbing, padding or cycling in cool (but not cold) weather - hard wearing, relatively inexpensive and superior grip) for foul-weather activities such as ice climbing, kiting and winter cycling.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157641626224314/"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7400/12800895193_08d09491b6_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>These are the previous version with red-starred palm, Rab seems to have updated the model briefly for this year. Based on the dry testing and the real use this weekend, they appear to be the ticket - warm enough while keeping the dexterity I need (i.e. fiddling with camera and other gadgets and gear). Durability remains to be proven, but they appear to be rugged overall - let&rsquo;s see how they will hold up during the upcoming season with various sports.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
