<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Myog | Leftbound]]></title>
  <link href="http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/categories/myog/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://leftbound.com/leftbound/"/>
  <updated>2018-01-25T00:34:54+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://leftbound.com/leftbound/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Joni Palomäki]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[joni@leftbound.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[MYOG - Monopod Pole]]></title>
    <link href="http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2017/01/11/MYOG-Monopod-Pole/"/>
    <updated>2017-01-11T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2017/01/11/MYOG-Monopod-Pole</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I don&rsquo;t own a real, full-size, tripod and actually haven&rsquo;t had one since I bought my first digital camera, back in 2001. I have however had a small selection of small tripods to carry around, when I need to rest the camera on something more sophisticated than a fence, tree branch or say, a pile of snow and a glove. Of those portables, Gorillapod has proven to be most versatile, though I&rsquo;ve had my share of trouble with them, breaking not just one, but two <a href="http://joby.com/gorillapod/gorillapod-hybrid">Hybrid</a>&rsquo;s during the last couple of years. A leg falling off in both cases, they were warranted by <a href="https://joby.com">Joby</a>, and today the Hybrid is still my go-to tripod for outdoors.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/31861482020/in/photostream/" title="Three tools"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/1/777/31861482020_d698e5630f_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Three threads"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>In addition to Joby, I have also held onto a <a href="http://www.industrialrev.com/ultrapod-i.html">Pedco Ultrapod I</a>. A superlight and small, and cheap, yet sturdy tripod, it has even held a full frame DSLR without flinching. And with the included velcro strap one can easily secure a smaller camera on a tree branch or similar sketchy platform. Third tripod I have is actually one without legs, the <a href="https://trailpix.myshopify.com">TrailPix Ultralight Tripod</a>. I got this off <a href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/1312251870/trailpix-ultralight-tripod">Kickstarter</a> back in 2013, but it hasn&rsquo;t really been used much.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/31410611684/in/datetaken/" title="Pedco Ultrapod I"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/1/610/31410611684_f66663cc18_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1536" alt="Pedco Ultrapod I"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The reason is mainly that in addition to utilizing two <em>short</em> poles you ought to have with you, it still needs a third one, typically a spare pole (if you carry one) or a separate aluminum pole. Of course a wooden stick would do as well. I have poles when going (telemark) skiing, cross country or nordic skating poles are simply too long if you consider the need for a third one, and on some of the longer hikes, but most of hiking, paddling, climbing and whatnot is done without any poles. So, while the product is actually very good, with legs locked in place with screws and a solid <a href="http://en.cnkingjoy.com/en/products.asp?id=145">Kingjoy BD-1</a> ballhead included, for me it&rsquo;s not a very convenient product to use. But mainly for the (removable) ballhead, I still hold on to it.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/32132807051/in/photostream/" title="TrailPix"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/1/264/32132807051_3b0efc7a64_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1536" alt="TrailPix"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>TrailPix aside, none of the above easily bring the camera higher up, or help take the camera further than an arms length, should you hold it in your hands. Years ago, around the time first GoPro&rsquo;s came out, I had been for some time wanting something taller/longer to screw a camera onto. Considering a monopod, I was also browsing the limited range of trekking poles meant for photographers. I quickly ditched the idea of a dedicated monopod as it would just have been another thing to carry. And having a perfectly good set of poles for different uses, it seemed wasteful to get another pair just to attach a camera to. Why not simply add a threaded bolt to an existing pole and be done with it?</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/31861478980/in/album-72157677052503772/" title="Gibron and Black Diamond handles"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/1/286/31861478980_ec88a3e556_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Gibron and Black Diamond handles"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>From idea to action, a visit to the local nuts and bolts specialty store (as the needed &frac14;-20 UNC threaded screws are not standard items in a typical hardware store in Finland) soon had me pulling off the handle on my Gibron Sherpa II telescopic pole. A pre-drilled hole through the top of the handle helped to screw in the threaded bolt from the inside of the handle, fixed in place with a knob of hot glue. Threaded through just the right amount to not bottom out on the camera, it worked perfectly.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/31861483160/in/photostream/" title="Gibron Sherpa II"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/261/31861483160_3b937015e0_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Gibron Sherpa II"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>For example the below video was shot using this pole and a GoPro, strapped on the bow, extending a meter or so outside of the canoe.</p>

<iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/31107186" width="770" height="433" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>As the Sherpa&rsquo;s were my skiing poles, I&rsquo;ve used them a lot as a monopod for family and group photos in the winter. Sticking a pole into firm snow, with a small(ish) camera threaded in, is solid enough to trust on, unless there&rsquo;s hard wind. In those cases I&rsquo;ve typically piled some snow around it, or pushed it in deeper, sometimes removing the basket. With the GoPro&rsquo;s coming into play, threading one at the end of the pole has been a fun way to shoot one another skiing down the slopes, being able to reach out close enough for interesting angles. And of course it works like charm for including yourself, but also more of the surroundings, in the picture or a video reportage, despite not having an ultra wide angle lens.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/31427092363/in/photostream/" title="Black Diamond Distance Carbon Z handle"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/1/570/31427092363_6b0b1d9d10_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Black Diamond Distance Carbon Z handle"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve since then done a similar work on two other pairs of poles I regularly use, both from Black Diamond. Traverse poles, great poles for ski touring by the way, were done the same way as the Gibron, first removing the handle by heating it - use hot water or a blow dryer. The strap comes off by pushing out a pin that locks it down, and it needs to be removed for drilling and threading in the bolt. It&rsquo;s a tight fit, but worked out fine, and once the bolt is securely in place, the strap can be re-attached without a fuzz. I opted to thread a nut on top, slightly recessed, which again was secured with a drop of hot glue.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/32103027202/in/dateposted/" title="Few tools required"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/1/279/32103027202_d36e8b8fd2_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Few tools required"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Latest modification was done on a pair of <a href="http://blackdiamondequipment.com/en/trekking-poles/distance-carbon-flz-pole-BD112176_cfg.html#sz=24&amp;start=30">Distance Carbon FLZ Trekking Poles</a> I had gotten for my trip to <a href="http://leftbound.com/blog/2015/07/13/Iceland-Revisited/">Iceland</a>, requiring a slightly different approach. I could not get the handles off from these, most likely since, made of EVA foam, they appear to be glued in. Being ultralight poles, the wrist straps are not bolted in, but are held by a string of nylon running though the handle, past the midpoint. As I couldn&rsquo;t remove it, and didn&rsquo;t want to accidentally cut it, I had to place the bolt way up front, and not being able to remove the handle and thread it in from below, the bolt had to go in head first from the top. Being made of soft foam, I just pre-drilled a large enough hole into the soft handle to squeece the bolt in. After dry testing, I pushed hot glue into the hole, and in went the bolt, EVA stretching out as needed for a snug fit.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/32199117536/in/photostream/" title="Black Diamond Distance Carbon Z"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/261/32199117536_b5340cb84e_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Black Diamond Distance Carbon FLZ"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>As you can see in the photo, I used a nut here as well, mainly due to the softness of the handle - this way, and with the hot glue filling, the assembly was secure and solid, not giving in at all. Used since last autumn, also this pole has worked well as a make-do monopod, and with my new pyramid tent, the pair will get out even more in the future. Quite a versatile piece of kit they have turned out to be - from trekking poles to amonopod to an adjustable center pole!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/31396369534/in/album-72157677052503772/" title="Flood happened"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/1/368/31396369534_08da1a2518_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Flood happened"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve mentioned GoPro, which can easily be connected to the pole with the Tripod Mount accessory, but similarly you can use many other accessories to hook up whatever recording device you need, including your mobile phone. My iPhone 6 never leaves the protective <a href="https://www.catalystlifestyle.com/collections/iphone6/products/copy-of-catalyst-case-for-iphone-6-black-space-gray">Catalyst Case</a>, and I&rsquo;ve got a <a href="https://www.catalystlifestyle.com/collections/frontpage/products/iphone-6-plus-6s-plus-multi-sport-mount">Multi-Sport Mount</a> to lock it down securely to any of my monopod poles.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/31861475980/in/album-72157677052503772/" title="GoPro Tripod Mount"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/1/568/31861475980_6b2add6471_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="GoPro Tripod Mount"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/31875538220/in/album-72157677052503772/" title="Multi-Sport Mount from Catalyst"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/1/541/31875538220_2237120d44_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Multi-Sport Mount from Catalyst"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Needless to say, these have been extremely useful modifications for me, and relatively simple to do, I can recommend them to anyone. If you already have a good pair of poles, I see no reason to invest into a new pair just to get the tripod mount. Not having to unscrew anything is a big plus in my books, as opposed to removable caps and whatnot seen on some of the dedicated products, essentially offering the same functionality in a bit more polished, though maybe over-engineered, package.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/32199118316/in/album-72157677052503772/" title="Three mounts"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/1/392/32199118316_0acadef9f9_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Three mounts"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>&#10095;&#10095; Flickr album: <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/albums/72157677052503772">MYOG - Monopod Pole</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[MYOG - Jetboil Hanging Kit]]></title>
    <link href="http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2015/04/10/MYOG-Jetboil-Hanging-Kit/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-10T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2015/04/10/MYOG-Jetboil-Hanging-Kit</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>While I prefer open fire over the glow and gentle roar of gas burner, and mostly use my <a href="http://leftbound.com/blog/2014/11/10/Bush-Buddy-Ultra/">Bush Buddy</a>, there are times when for example a simple personal cooking system (PCS) like the Jetboil stoves, or say, <a href="http://www.cascadedesigns.com/msr/stoves/stove-systems/windboiler/product">MSR Windboiler</a> or <a href="https://www.alpkit.com/products/brukit">Alpkit BruKit</a>, is more convenient choice. Even during winter, with <a href="http://www.primus.eu/winter-gas-230-g">winter spec&rsquo;d cartridges</a> and suitable butane/propane mixes, they are a good and clean option. Coldest weather I have used gas in was on a 4-day ski touring in Kebnekaise, Sweden. Back then, we ran a free standing, hosed gas stove with Primus Power Gas (25% propane, 25% isobutane and 50% butane), in around -25 degrees celcius temperatures. Recycling few canisters in and out of our down jackets and having them upside down and on top of the kettle we managed to melt snow and boil all the water we needed at our base camp. Not the most efficient system, and surely a liquid fuel stove would have fared better, had we had one at our disposal at the time.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/17066907316/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7708/17066907316_ec26230ca8_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Lately, as far as the gas stoves go, I have been using a tiny, 48-gram titanium canister stove, <a href="http://www.backpacker.com/stoves-and-cookware/stoves/gear-review-monatauk-gnat-stove/">Monatauk Gnat</a>, which I bought some five years ago. It has been useful until these days especially as a backup for the Bush Buddy, when &lsquo;open&rsquo; fire is not feasible. Couple of weeks back, not searching for one in particular, I ran across a great deal for an odd Jetboil Sol (69.90 EUR only). Having tried out some of the early versions and with few friends currently using some other, later models, I jumped on it. The one I got was missing the <a href="http://www.jetboil.com/Products/Pot-Support/">pot support accessory</a> and neither had the fancy heat indicator on the insulating cozy, neither of which I needed anyway. It does have the updated pietzo igniter and regulator, so it is one of the more recent versions. Sol is apparently EOL with <a href="http://www.jetboil.com/Products/Compare-Cooking-Systems/?ps=all">Zip remaining as the smallest volume PCS</a> in their range, but at least <a href="http://www.xxl.fi/retkeily-era/retkiruokailu/retkikeittimet/jetboil-jetboil-sol-aluminium-retkikeitin/p/1101575_1_style">XXL</a> in Scandinavia still sells them, for a fair price.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649528805714/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7620/17066530826_dc85da7953_z.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>With the new cooking system in the house, I decided I would build a hanging kit for it, to be able to secure the tippy, especially without the included fuel canister stabilizer, system from a tree branch or tent pole if so needed. <a href="http://www.jetboil.com/Accessories/Kits/">Jetboil does have hanging kits as an accessory</a>, but I was after something more simple (and cheaper). I had few ideas when walking to the local hardware store to get some thin, 1 mm wire rope and crimps, and once at home, experimenting a bit, I put together a suspension system what I believe is simple yet robust and functional.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649528805714/"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8776/17066531076_59088930fd_z.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649528805714/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7648/17066530656_faac68fd59_z.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649528805714/"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8765/16904935470_e6bb951a53_z.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>With the insulating cozy, the wire system is mostly hidden from the plain sight, keeping the system clutter-free. I had a threaded wire loop laying around, so I used that as a retainer if dropping the burner while fiddling with the stove would be a problem.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649528805714/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7670/16472341783_fc38a717b2_z.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649528805714/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7642/17091799221_056ff10836_z.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>I stress tested the system with roughly 3 kilograms of weight to make sure the crimps especially do not slip under a maximum normal load. With the single loop, suspended from two points only, filling the pot, closing the lid and eventually pouring out the boiling liquid, all while being hung, is a breeze. Also, the pot stays upright even without the cartridge or burner attached, so it is safe for example to change the cartridge while the pot is full of hot water.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649528805714/"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8730/16904934930_b7d9b2658d_z.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649528805714/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7590/16904713958_07d7688404_z.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>When not needed, the hanging kit can be simply wrapped and stored under the insulating cozy, from where it is easily deployed again. Or, it can be stuffed into the pot as the thin wiring will not interfere with the lid and it closes just fine. As the complete wiring, with the keyring and retainer loop for the burner, weighs a mere 10 grams, making it permanently attached was no brainer. A removable system would have been both heavier and bulkier, adding more possible points of failure.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649528805714/"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8763/16904714038_d5fff35848_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>If you have a Jetboil or other similar PCS, and would need to hang it up every now and then, consider rigging something like this. It should be relatively simple to adapt this idea for example into one of the aforementioned competing systems. And as setting this up, at least on a Jetboil Sol, required no modifications to the stove itself, this should not in normal circumstances void the warranty.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
