<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Stoves | Leftbound]]></title>
  <link href="http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/categories/stoves/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://leftbound.com/leftbound/"/>
  <updated>2019-08-13T01:06:21+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://leftbound.com/leftbound/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Joni Palomäki]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[joni@leftbound.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[MYOG - Jetboil Hanging Kit]]></title>
    <link href="http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2015/04/10/MYOG-Jetboil-Hanging-Kit/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-10T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2015/04/10/MYOG-Jetboil-Hanging-Kit</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>While I prefer open fire over the glow and gentle roar of gas burner, and mostly use my <a href="http://leftbound.com/blog/2014/11/10/Bush-Buddy-Ultra/">Bush Buddy</a>, there are times when for example a simple personal cooking system (PCS) like the Jetboil stoves, or say, <a href="http://www.cascadedesigns.com/msr/stoves/stove-systems/windboiler/product">MSR Windboiler</a> or <a href="https://www.alpkit.com/products/brukit">Alpkit BruKit</a>, is more convenient choice. Even during winter, with <a href="http://www.primus.eu/winter-gas-230-g">winter spec&rsquo;d cartridges</a> and suitable butane/propane mixes, they are a good and clean option. Coldest weather I have used gas in was on a 4-day ski touring in Kebnekaise, Sweden. Back then, we ran a free standing, hosed gas stove with Primus Power Gas (25% propane, 25% isobutane and 50% butane), in around -25 degrees celcius temperatures. Recycling few canisters in and out of our down jackets and having them upside down and on top of the kettle we managed to melt snow and boil all the water we needed at our base camp. Not the most efficient system, and surely a liquid fuel stove would have fared better, had we had one at our disposal at the time.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/17066907316/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7708/17066907316_ec26230ca8_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Lately, as far as the gas stoves go, I have been using a tiny, 48-gram titanium canister stove, <a href="http://www.backpacker.com/stoves-and-cookware/stoves/gear-review-monatauk-gnat-stove/">Monatauk Gnat</a>, which I bought some five years ago. It has been useful until these days especially as a backup for the Bush Buddy, when &lsquo;open&rsquo; fire is not feasible. Couple of weeks back, not searching for one in particular, I ran across a great deal for an odd Jetboil Sol (69.90 EUR only). Having tried out some of the early versions and with few friends currently using some other, later models, I jumped on it. The one I got was missing the <a href="http://www.jetboil.com/Products/Pot-Support/">pot support accessory</a> and neither had the fancy heat indicator on the insulating cozy, neither of which I needed anyway. It does have the updated pietzo igniter and regulator, so it is one of the more recent versions. Sol is apparently EOL with <a href="http://www.jetboil.com/Products/Compare-Cooking-Systems/?ps=all">Zip remaining as the smallest volume PCS</a> in their range, but at least <a href="http://www.xxl.fi/retkeily-era/retkiruokailu/retkikeittimet/jetboil-jetboil-sol-aluminium-retkikeitin/p/1101575_1_style">XXL</a> in Scandinavia still sells them, for a fair price.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649528805714/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7620/17066530826_dc85da7953_z.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>With the new cooking system in the house, I decided I would build a hanging kit for it, to be able to secure the tippy, especially without the included fuel canister stabilizer, system from a tree branch or tent pole if so needed. <a href="http://www.jetboil.com/Accessories/Kits/">Jetboil does have hanging kits as an accessory</a>, but I was after something more simple (and cheaper). I had few ideas when walking to the local hardware store to get some thin, 1 mm wire rope and crimps, and once at home, experimenting a bit, I put together a suspension system what I believe is simple yet robust and functional.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649528805714/"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8776/17066531076_59088930fd_z.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649528805714/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7648/17066530656_faac68fd59_z.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649528805714/"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8765/16904935470_e6bb951a53_z.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>With the insulating cozy, the wire system is mostly hidden from the plain sight, keeping the system clutter-free. I had a threaded wire loop laying around, so I used that as a retainer if dropping the burner while fiddling with the stove would be a problem.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649528805714/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7670/16472341783_fc38a717b2_z.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649528805714/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7642/17091799221_056ff10836_z.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>I stress tested the system with roughly 3 kilograms of weight to make sure the crimps especially do not slip under a maximum normal load. With the single loop, suspended from two points only, filling the pot, closing the lid and eventually pouring out the boiling liquid, all while being hung, is a breeze. Also, the pot stays upright even without the cartridge or burner attached, so it is safe for example to change the cartridge while the pot is full of hot water.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649528805714/"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8730/16904934930_b7d9b2658d_z.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649528805714/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7590/16904713958_07d7688404_z.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>When not needed, the hanging kit can be simply wrapped and stored under the insulating cozy, from where it is easily deployed again. Or, it can be stuffed into the pot as the thin wiring will not interfere with the lid and it closes just fine. As the complete wiring, with the keyring and retainer loop for the burner, weighs a mere 10 grams, making it permanently attached was no brainer. A removable system would have been both heavier and bulkier, adding more possible points of failure.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649528805714/"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8763/16904714038_d5fff35848_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>If you have a Jetboil or other similar PCS, and would need to hang it up every now and then, consider rigging something like this. It should be relatively simple to adapt this idea for example into one of the aforementioned competing systems. And as setting this up, at least on a Jetboil Sol, required no modifications to the stove itself, this should not in normal circumstances void the warranty.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bush Buddy Ultra]]></title>
    <link href="http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2014/11/10/Bush-Buddy-Ultra/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-10T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2014/11/10/Bush-Buddy-Ultra</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In 2012 I started to look into options to cut down the use of my waste inducing gas stove, and while liquid fuel stoves would work (and also built one of those <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/15735538166/">DIY meth stoves</a>, out of two cans of Red Bull), I was quickly drawn by the idea of wood burning stoves and did some simple but empowering trials of DIY stoves to get myself started.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649164941106/"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3953/15734766006_010d387820_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>While my own builds consisted merely of tin cans with ventilation and feeding holes cut into them, more advanced commercial products were already available, and after a closer look to some of those online, I decided to get a Canadian cottage product, a <a href="http://bushbuddy.ca">Bush Buddy</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649164941106/"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5605/15573106838_f7185fb288_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649164941106/"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8408/15756546461_1dd50c3da7_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Bush Buddy is a product of Fritz Handel, handmade in <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iskut">Iskut</a>. While relying on the proven concept of double-walled downdraft gasifier, mr. Handel has succeeded in creating a compact and lightweight, yet very functional product, that still today is a reference for similar stoves (and sadly also for few ripped off replicas). It&rsquo;s made of stainless steel of varying thickness and as far as I can see, no changes to the physical dimensions or features have been made since I purchased mine.</p>

<p>The stove is today available directly from Fritz himself at <a href="http://bushbuddy.ca">Bushbuddy.ca</a>, and also from his apprentice Jeff at <a href="http://www.nomadicstovecompany.com">Nomadic Stove Company</a>, who currently sells three versions of the stove: Trekker with 0.08" outer shell, and two Ultra versions with 0.06" and 0.04" outer shells. My stove is the 0.04" Ultra.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649164941106/"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3941/15573003568_752c28150e_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Since purchasing this stove, I have hardly used anything else, be it for brewing a cup of coffee, simmering a bowl of risotto or simply boiling water for a freeze dried meal. Consuming little fuel - few handful of twigs will boil you a pot of water - it is low impact and as the bottom does not heat up, it leaves behind nothing but a pinch of ash.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649164941106/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7491/15573616830_618ffd49f0_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>As for the wear and tear in two and a half years I&rsquo;ve had it, looking very closely, I can find a ding or two from knocking it over or rolling it down a rock, but aside of the typical soot and coloring of metal from the heat, it is as good as new. As this is the slimmest model, the walls do give in if pressed lightly, but spring back up when released, leaving no permanent deformation. It is recommended to wrap a cloth around the stove while stored inside the pot, but I haven&rsquo;t felt the need to take such precaution. There is absolutely no signs of corrosion and all the welds and joints are intact - and I have not been babying it. Hence I can attest that, unless you use it as a hammer, it could easily be a life-long purchase.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649164941106/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7570/15139018623_edd0fc9230_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Carrying your Bush Buddy is made easy by selecting appropriately sized pot to store it in. I use a 1100 ml Tibetan Titanium pot which is a perfect fit. This pot, as far as I know, is no longer available, but you should not have problems finding a suitable pot, as the diameter of the Bush Buddy is (smartly) the same as a 230 g and 450 g (threaded) gas cartridges. Often pots are made to take in one of these and if yours holds a 450 g cartridge also height-wise, it&rsquo;s a sure fit also for the Bush Buddy (which is just a tad shorter).</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649164941106/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7517/15734721016_0e520fb6ba_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>When I suspect I might have trouble finding fuel for the wood stove or wish to have a backup, I also bring in a tiny titanium gas stove (Monatauk Gnat), which folds inside the Bush Buddy. A <a href="http://www.lightmyfire.com/products/products/swedish-firesteel-20.aspx">fire steel</a> and a selection of tinder (or pre-cut twigs) also fits inside, completing a full kit stoved in a DIY cuben fiber sack - plus one of those half-emptied gas cartridges I still have lying around, carried separately if needed. For tinder, I bring pieces of tar infused wood (tervas, in Finnish), some cotton balls mixed with petroleum jelly and couple of Esbit solid fuel tablets, all of which can be lit up easily with fire steel.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649164941106/"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8272/15138466334_0ac500a2c5_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649164941106/"><img src="https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3953/15139018693_3658aa0646_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649164941106/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7493/15573616780_a322fc79b1_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>If you are in the market for a wood burning stove, Bush Buddy should be very high on your list. And if you choose to buy one, make sure you get it directly from <a href="http://bushbuddy.ca">Fritz</a> or from <a href="http://www.nomadicstovecompany.com">Nomadic Stove Company</a>, accepting no substitutes. To learn a bit more about the man behind the product, read the <a href="http://hikinginfinland.com/2009/11/interview-fritz-handel-from-bushbuddy.html">interview at Hiking in Finland</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649164941106/"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5608/15138466544_8f875d7a42_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
