<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Bikerafting | Leftbound]]></title>
  <link href="http://leftbound.com/blog/categories/bikerafting/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://leftbound.com/"/>
  <updated>2020-01-09T21:58:52+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://leftbound.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Joni Palomäki]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[joni@leftbound.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Medvastö Bikerafting]]></title>
    <link href="http://leftbound.com/blog/Medvasto-Bikerafting/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-17T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://leftbound.com/blog/Medvasto-Bikerafting</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>What a great weekend outdoors! I was taking it easy last week after catching a tiny cold (perhaps something to do with <a href="http://leftbound.com/blog/2012/09/13/Wet-But-Not-Miserable/">last weekend&rsquo;s paddle in the rain</a>, and was eager to get out on the weekend, catching up on all the missed opportunities. Luckily the weather was simply great, with the Friday night storm and all.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157641626259334/"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2875/12800789815_8d5a112837_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>One of the outings I did during the weekend was a bikerafting trip to Kirkkonummi on Saturday, a roundtrip which originally aimed to visit <a href="https://maps.google.fi/maps?q=pentala&amp;hl=fi&amp;sll=60.20676,24.675114&amp;sspn=0.339808,1.234589&amp;hnear=Pentala&amp;t=m&amp;z=14">Pentala</a> (and to view <a href="http://www.surffitalli.com/content/view/1067/78/">windsurfers racing around the island</a> on the way), but starting late I had to change a plan a bit on the fly to make it back home in time for family duties.</p>

<iframe width="600" height="450" frameborder="0" scrolling="no" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" src="https://maps.google.com/maps/ms?msa=0&amp;msid=206947131455056057448.0004c9cd55e3c5fcad436&amp;hl=en&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;t=m&amp;source=embed&amp;ll=60.123211,24.608002&amp;spn=0.08209,0.219727&amp;output=embed"></iframe>


<p>(View Medvastö Bikerafting route in a <a href="https://maps.google.com/maps/ms?msa=0&amp;amp;msid=206947131455056057448.0004c9cd55e3c5fcad436&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;t=m&amp;amp;source=embed&amp;amp;ll=60.123211,24.608002&amp;amp;spn=0.08209,0.219727">larger map</a>)</p>

<p>I kicked off from Saunalahti in the early afternoon, cycling through Sarfvik golf course, and aiming towards Långviken. Fields next to the quiet (closed) forest roads where spotted with grazing cows and horses, and sightings of deer (roes and white-tailed deer are plentiful in the area) were common - almost ran over one, jumping from the bushes on the road just in front of me.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157641626259334/"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7327/12801212714_cffab66897_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157641626259334/"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5480/12800789785_5f7019bc50_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.ymparisto.fi/default.asp?contentid=10769&amp;lan=fi">Medvastö-Stormossen</a> area with its groves and wetlands belongs to Natura 2000 ecological network of protected areas. Most of Medvastö&rsquo;s shoreline outside Natura is privately owned and hence closed, but I was able to locate an open pier from where to paddle out. While discussing about packrafts and fatbikes with an older couple who was spending time on a rental cottage (owned by police actually) nearby, I stacked the bike on the bow, and headed out. Realizing the late start and hearing no windsurfers had been seen so far, decided to skip Pentala this time (there&rsquo;s a small lake on the island, with another island in it - something I would like to visit in a better time), and with a brisk wind behind my back took a bearing towards Ljusskär.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157641626259334/"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3721/12801212514_0274c90fbd_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157641626259334/"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7411/12800789655_213d84eb0e_o.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Weather was nothing like the night before, but paddling was fun with tailwind, and waves stirred up by large boats passing by - sunshine did not make it any harder either. On the Björköfjärden inlet there&rsquo;s a nice small surf a distance from the shore, due to a small area of shallow sea bed. I stopped on an islet populated by barnacle geese, and got a sighting of crane on a pier nearby.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157641626259334/"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7431/12800898003_a43932df8f_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Southwest wind was picking up, now working against me when I headed past Ljusskär to Björkö - large coastguard boat cruised past while I fought the wind and whitecapped waves pushing the boat from the side. After Björkö I headed more or less downwind towards Småholmarna, and continued past Laurinlahti to Kivenlahti, where I went ashore, packed up, and cycled home.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157641626259334/"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5510/12800781395_a3d3863a2c_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157641626259334/"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7308/12801211984_963909470e_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>In addition to Pentala, southwest from Medvastö there&rsquo;s a plethora of tiny islands and islets which would be good spots for an overnighter, similar to what I&rsquo;ve thought of doing in Porkkala, possibly still this autumn.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bikerafting in Suvisaaristo]]></title>
    <link href="http://leftbound.com/blog/Bikerafting-In-Suvisaaristo/"/>
    <updated>2012-06-29T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://leftbound.com/blog/Bikerafting-In-Suvisaaristo</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Had a couple of hours free time, and headed to Suvisaaristo by bike to paddle a bit on the sunny sea. Weather was way good for any serious trial for the packraft-fatbike combo, but the backwash from larger boats running too close already revealed it to be quite tipsy, and wasn&rsquo;t eager to find out how it would be (im)possible to turn the package around once capsized (need to try it at some point on shallow water though).</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157641624886913/"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7340/12801153884_f1efb0766b_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>I rode to <a href="http://goo.gl/maps/sVkX">Hyljelahti</a> and inflated the raft on the nearby beach, and toured around the Ryssjeholmen and Granholmen islands, and then headed to Matasaari, where I found the narrow passage between the mainland and the island, just fitting under the small bridge with my payload.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157641624886913/"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5496/12800840643_33758546f3_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>I first had planned to paddle through the <a href="http://goo.gl/maps/GG8e">Svinö sund</a>, but the traffic was pretty intensive, with big boats coming out through the narrow channel pretty fast (despite the speed limit&hellip;), and I bailed out, wanting to prevent capsizing the raft at a tricky spot.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157641624886913/"><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5521/12801148454_2f0e961420_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Packed up and on the bike again, I hit the Hanikka trails and duckboards, and continued back home, fun little outing in the neighborhood!</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157641624886913/"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7367/12800732915_dd330b2a4c_o.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
