<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Bikepacking | Leftbound]]></title>
  <link href="http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/categories/bikepacking/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://leftbound.com/leftbound/"/>
  <updated>2019-08-13T01:12:06+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://leftbound.com/leftbound/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Joni Palomäki]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[joni@leftbound.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Peeping at the Packraft Gathering]]></title>
    <link href="http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2016/09/21/Peeping-At-The-Packraft-Gathering/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-21T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2016/09/21/Peeping-At-The-Packraft-Gathering</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last weekend the annual packraft gathering took place in southern Finland. Now third year in running, it pulled together around 15 paddlers over the course of the weekend, a highest number so far, with several first timers and lots of new faces. As opposed to <a href="http://leftbound.com/blog/2015/11/19/Packraft-Gathering/">last year&rsquo;s lake hopping in Helvetinjärvi National Park</a>, this time the event was kicked off in <a href="http://www.kytaja-usmi.fi">Kytäjä-Usmi</a> outdoor area in Hyvinkää, and took the colorful flock of paddlers down the river Vantaanjoki, all the way to Myllykoski, and a few, even beyond.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/29838062175/in/album-72157672979293280/" title="Colors of packrafting"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/9/8307/29838062175_c568bb7162_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1536" alt="Colors of packrafting"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Unfortunately, for me, come the week of the event, I managed to pull something on my left shoulder, playing sporty games at my daughter&rsquo;s school camp I was supervising, and had to make a tough call of bailing out from the longish paddled down the river, and simply join the kick-off at lake Piilolammi in Kytäjä-Usmi, to meet the fellow paddlers and to try catch some fish. Launch was preceded by a simple workshop we had put together with Marko, discussing the few intricacies of fishing from a packraft, and preparing simple line and a hook systems to use with earthworms or bait fish. Although lake offered no catch for the minimalist fishermen, a dark-hued pike was eventually caught in the group, and prepared by the fire.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/29724989062/in/album-72157672979293280/" title="Pikey dinner being prepared"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/9/8514/29724989062_9a2d08e82e_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1536" alt="Pikey dinner being prepared"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Some of us, yours truly included, had relied on catching some protein from the lake, so the lone catch quickly disappeared from the pan, with some fried onion and chopped sheep polypore (&lsquo;lampaankääpä&rsquo;), harvested from the surrounding forest, as a side dish. I had mistakenly assumed there would be a lean-to at the lake, so without any shelter with me, I laid my sleeping bag by the fire, bivvying under the cloudy skies, perfectly warm and cozy through the relatively warm autumn night.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/29838065235/in/album-72157672979293280/" title="Journey begins"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/9/8492/29838065235_2c880726a2_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1536" alt="Journey begins"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Next morning I tried again to catch some perch for breakfast but the lake, rich in humus, still provided none, so porridge it was. The merry team of packrafters then packed up, few heads stronger, and hit the road, hiking to a nearby tributary, for an early launch towards Vantaanjoki. Left behind by my own choise, I had opted to explore the area on a bike, and packing up with day&rsquo;s supplies and fishing gear, I hit the trails soon after, with a rough plan for a round trip through the forest roads and trails.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/29755491901/in/album-72157672979293280/" title="Faster!"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/9/8345/29755491901_d55fccbeeb_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Faster!"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Day remained cloudy and comfortably cool, while I roamed in the park on my fatbike, visiting several lakes, including Mäkiperänlampi, Kiiskilampi, Iso Kypärä, Kaksoislammit and Usminjärvi. Of these, the middle three have a lean-to in them, and especially the ones in Kiiskilampi and Kaksoislammit are well positioned with great views. A smart approach in my opinion, the firewood supplies, which there are many, were always positioned some distance away from the lean-to&rsquo;s and fireplaces, requiring a bit of effort to keep the fire going.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/29210839154/in/album-72157672979293280/" title="Woody supply"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/9/8393/29210839154_d3af583fba_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Woody supply"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Not so smart choice were the oddly sized lean-tos, sized to accommodate only three people at a time, with anyone over 160 cm tall having to sleep in parallel to the doorway, effectively blocking the way for others sharing the shelter. A 195 cm tall myself, it was not a match made in heaven, as head or feet first is generally the best way to share a lean-to shelter.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/29545303730/in/album-72157672979293280/" title="Too tall, or too small?"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/9/8551/29545303730_7b91349198_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Too tall, or too small?"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I took my time to enjoy the views, to stop here and there, and of course to try catch some fish, as my lunch was mainly dependent on that. Lakes remained silent, which has to do with, if not only my luck, or skills, the specific time of the year and the northerly winds. Regardless, no protein from the lake, but I did have a few slices of buckwheat bread with garnish in my pack and shared a sausage by the fire at Iso Kypärä, offered by a friendly couple finishing up their lunch. If the nature does not provide, a kind passer-by just might! Though I did find some more mushrooms and of course plenty of harvest-ready lingonberries and some overdue bilberries.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/29212062423/in/album-72157672979293280/" title="Lingonberries are ripe"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/9/8419/29212062423_4b7981b8da_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Lingonberries are ripe"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/29838084795/in/album-72157672979293280/" title="Last of the bilberries"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/9/8023/29838084795_4d6390b5b7_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Last of the bilberries"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The park had just recently received brand new sign-posts all around, which made it super easy to navigate through, with directions and distances carved in each colorful pole. These however were only along the gravel and forest roads, so once on the trails, a general sense of direction, and at times a map of the area, was needed for navigation.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/29210829804/in/album-72157672979293280/" title="Signpost"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/9/8270/29210829804_e08d19b26f_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Signpost"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/29838078205/in/album-72157672979293280/" title="Turn left here"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/9/8104/29838078205_61e271d758_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Turn left here"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I finished my tour nearby lake Piilolammi, where my car was parked, and guestimating the group just might be done soon with their roughly 20 kilometers of paddling down the river, I deciced to, instead of heading directly home, visit them at the next stop, at Nukarinkoski rapids. Turning up around six in the evening to the lean-to, the group had indeed shortly arrived. Similar to few others joining the event, I hadn&rsquo;t had high expectations on the surroundings of Vantaanjoki, and having to skip the long paddle had not been a huge disappointment. However, as I got to hear around the camp fire, the river had an ace or two up in its sleeve, and the day had not only been a long strenuous paddle with a good mileage for slow packrafts, but spotted with interesting views and passing attractions.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/29210838154/in/album-72157672979293280/" title="The nest"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/9/8531/29210838154_766373f1a8_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="The nest"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>While the easy rapids down the line had been rock-hopping gardens due to very low water levels, and the big ones at Nukarinkoski (largest of them all along Vantaanjoki), and next day at Myllykoski, unpaddleable again due to insufficient discharge, they had made the days more interesting and also revealed some good potential for a revisit in the future. I bid farewell again to the team at the night fall, heading home with few others, while the remaining packrafters were looking forward to the next day&rsquo;s paddle.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/29210845494/in/album-72157672979293280/" title="Serene pond of Kaksoislammit"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/9/8330/29210845494_f0464af89e_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Serene pond of Kaksoislammit"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/29210847044/in/album-72157672979293280/" title="On the steep"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/9/8387/29210847044_255ed047c0_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="On the steep"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The outdoorsmen and -women, packraft-nutties, pleased to meet you all! Looking forward to the next annual, or perhaps soon biannual, meeting. For more visuals from the actual event, browse through <a href="http://caide.kuvat.fi/kuvat/Hiking,+Packrafting+and+Fishing+/Packrafting+Gathering+Vantaanjoki/">Caj&rsquo;s photos</a>. Since this summer, we also have a <a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/1760898697500487/">Facebook group</a> to bring together all packrafters in Finland - feel free to join that, or one of the other local of international groups that already exist, to keep yourself informed on what&rsquo;s what in packrafting.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/29838076035/in/album-72157672979293280/" title="Fireplace at Kiiskilampi"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/9/8535/29838076035_945096dcee_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Fireplace at Kiiskilampi"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>&#10095;&#10095; Flickr album (with more photos from Kytäjä-Usmi): <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/albums/72157672979293280">Peeping at the Packraft Gathering</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lauhanvuori National Park by Bike]]></title>
    <link href="http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2016/08/31/Lauhanvuori-National-Park-By-Bike/"/>
    <updated>2016-08-31T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2016/08/31/Lauhanvuori-National-Park-By-Bike</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Each time I visit family and relatives in Ostrobothnia, I try to reserve some time to head outdoors and visit interesting places hiking, paddling, cycling or whatever is appropriate for the given season. One of the gems I found this summer was the <a href="http://www.luontoon.fi/lauhanvuori">Lauhanvuori National Park</a>, southwest of Kauhajoki, which I visited by bike in July.</p>

<p>Best known as having the highest &lsquo;mountain&rsquo; (a true mountain indeed in the scale of Ostrobothnia) in Western Finland, rising 231 meters above sea level, and of its ancient seashores, called &lsquo;kivijata&rsquo; or &lsquo;jata&rsquo;, this national park extends across roughly 54 square kilometers of hardwood forest with podsolic soil, with springs, ponds and small lakes to enjoy, and of course those aforementioned boulderfields and different types of bog.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/29312007926/in/album-72157669993821174/" title="Ahvenlammi"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/9/8399/29312007926_50da84139b_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Ahvenlammi"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Uncommon within the current 39 national parks in Finland, cycling on the trails is luckily not forbidden in this particular national park, but <a href="http://www.luontoon.fi/lauhanvuori/aktiviteetit">cautiously encouraged</a> within the well-established (and sign-posted) network of trails. As several <a href="https://www.imba.com/resources/research/trail-science/environmental-impacts-mountain-biking-science-review-and-best-practices">studies have concluded</a>, mountain biking generally has an (environmental) impact that is less than or comparable to hiking, but one should still thread carefully to avoid any unnecessary conflicts. Bikepacking style of exploration though is less likely to cause friction. During my visit I had only positive encounters with hikers (while I saw no other cyclists), part of which might be due to riding a fatbike, part to my chatty personality, and the rest surely due to the merry folks of Ostrobothnia!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/29058292300/in/album-72157669993821174/" title="Restored duckboards"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/9/8215/29058292300_6882c4acc0_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Restored duckboards"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>During the day I was mostly alone, as I only met few hikers at the trailend and close to the central parking lot, not far from the lookout tower. Just a sample of one day over one weekend, I did have a short talk with a family, regular visitors themselves, who confirmed park really does not seem to get a whole lot visitors, outside of the parking lot surroundings - what a shame.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/29266773181/in/album-72157669993821174/" title="Watchtower view"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/9/8502/29266773181_08c92ce3a3_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Watchtower view"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Spending a full day on the trail, from dawn till dusk, I got to cycle most of all rideable trails across the park, some 40+ kilometers in total, plus some on the gravel roads, connecting few trailheads. I did not carry a map of the area, but followed the generally well-marked trails and checked my bearings on the GPS, when I was not sure which direction best to take. In addition to marked routes leading to specific attraction or a vantage point, there are plenty of trails to go about and around, so that&rsquo;s exactly what I did.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/29266787861/in/album-72157669993821174/" title="Line of sight"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/9/8063/29266787861_03ce8877eb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Line of sight"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Taking my time to stop and enjoy the varied scenes, and to harvest an ample amount of billberies and raspberries as I came across good spots, I rode anything from overgrown forest roads (doubletracks really) and well maintained duckboards to technical single track and fast-paced trails. I was especially enchanted by the small sand-bottomed creeks, populated by brown trouts (fishing not permitted), with chrystal clear waters and mesmerizing views such as this churning sand in a tiny pond (video in <a href="https://www.youtube.com/embed/WleZAaZfcYQ">Youtube</a>):</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/29266818301/in/album-72157669993821174/" title="Mesmerizing sand"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/9/8249/29266818301_ea1bbb2cf2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Mesmerizing sand"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Easiest trails were around the Lauhanvuori lookout tower and around the lake Spitaalijärvi and Kaivolammi pond, and heading southwest, kilometers long network of duckboards greets the visitor, providing access across bogs and into the boulderfields.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/29345567745/in/album-72157669993821174/" title="Along a sandy river"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/9/8503/29345567745_2f72068134_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Along a sandy river"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/28722537934/in/album-72157669993821174/" title="Long and windy road"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/9/8475/28722537934_1dfe7c7bd8_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Long and windy road"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Towards west, around Lauhansarvi and Huhtakorpi is where I found the narrowest and most technical trails, and also some, hopefully about to be restored, broken down duckboards, before arriving to Ahvenlammi pond. There are few springs in the park, to quench your thirst in - I filled my reserves in Huhtakorpi spring.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/29266838321/in/album-72157669993821174/" title="Quenching the thirst"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/9/8385/29266838321_a551393bf2_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Quenching the thirst"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Ahvenlammi used to be the camping spot north of the area, a serene mire of a lake, but the fireplace there is about to be torn down, and new site established at another pond, aforementioned Kaivolammi. As the fireplace was still intact, with a poster informing about the upcoming change, I had my dinner there, before continuing my circle around the park as the sun was setting, and to have a post-ride dip in the Spitaalijärvi (&lsquo;Leprocy Lake&rsquo;). Lake Spitaalijärvi is an acidic lake with pH as low as 4.7, with presumed healing properties - hence the name.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/29058315000/in/album-72157669993821174/" title="Boulderfields"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8207/29058315000_644d245bbb_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Boulderfields"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>A great long day on a bike, glad I picked this one up for one of the summer outings and I highly recommend it for a daytrip or an overnighter on a bike. Map of the area and some other vital pieces of information can be found <a href="http://www.luontoon.fi/lauhanvuori">here</a>. Similar to few other destinations in this area I&rsquo;ve visited in the past (<a href="http://leftbound.com/blog/2014/04/23/Suupohja-Sample/">1</a>, <a href="http://leftbound.com/blog/2015/04/07/Nuijapoloku/">2</a>), also this one is featured in the <a href="http://www.seikkailesuupohjassa.fi/en">Seikkaile Suupohjassa</a> -resource, maintained by <a href="http://www.suupohjankehittamisyhdistys.fi">Suupohja Development Association</a> (Suupohjan Kehittämisyhdistys ry).</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/28724420593/in/album-72157669993821174/" title="Bogtastic cycling"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/9/8880/28724420593_3c49a47481_b.jpg" width="1024" height="683" alt="Bogtastic cycling"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/28722564944/in/album-72157669993821174/" title="Consumed by fire"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8415/28722564944_dd88af093c_b.jpg" width="1024" height="768" alt="Consumed by fire"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>&#10095;&#10095; Flickr album (with more photos): <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/albums/72157669993821174">Lauhanvuori National Park by Bike</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Meiko Go Round]]></title>
    <link href="http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2015/03/29/Meiko-Go-Round/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-29T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2015/03/29/Meiko-Go-Round</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This weekend I was supposed to join a few paddlers to explore the <a href="http://kansalaisen.karttapaikka.fi/kartanhaku/osoitehaku.html?x=363295&amp;y=6697156&amp;srs=EPSG:3067&amp;text=H%C3%A4rk%C3%A4l%C3%A4njoen+aloituspaikka&amp;scale=16000&amp;action=link&amp;mode=&amp;lang=fi">Härkälänjoki</a> river, which would have also been the season&rsquo;s opening for me. But unexpected duties called and I had to bail out at the last minute. Others went, read about the wallow'y paddle in <a href="https://avisuora.wordpress.com/2015/03/28/melontaa-ja-rypemista-harkalanjoessa-28-3-2015/">Janne&rsquo;s blog</a> (in Finnish).</p>

<p>Vexed, spending most of Saturday indoors (weather was pretty miserable, so not a huge loss though), come Sunday I packed the bike and hit the road. Decided against paddling, traditional season&rsquo;s opening in Espoonjoki river can wait, I rode to Kirkkonummi to cycle around lake Meiko.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649311720663/"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8754/16781278390_af2d0616f4_z.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Meiko is a nice wilderness area and, being just some 20 kilometers away, one of my regular destinations, be it for hiking, paddling or cycling. Despite visiting the area many times, many of the trails covered, I had never completed a full roundtrip around the meandering lake. I knew that the south side of the lake would be rather technical and tricky to cycle, and my bike loaded up with some bare essentials for a day out, I expected to push the bike quite a bit.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649311720663/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7585/16782556229_89d291d29d_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Once I arrived to the outdoor area, I headed to the Korsolampi fireplace to collect some sticks and twigs for my Bushbuddy.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649311720663/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7628/16781277550_67562d0285_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>I circled the lake clockwise, and as it turned out, the trail, mostly following the shoreline, was not overly difficult. At the end of the day I estimated that I probably rode about 90 percent of it. Some pushing and pulling, and lifting the bike over random obstacles such as fallen trees was perfectly acceptable.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649311720663/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7604/16782557229_de77659be6_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>I enjoyed a long lunch on top of a cliff on the south side of the lake, with a view, and despite the gloomy skies not a drop of rain fell, and even sun peeped out when I was cycling back home. Yet another fun day out in Meiko, maybe next time the ice will all be gone, and it&rsquo;s time to pull out the packraft and start catching some fish!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649311720663/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7629/16967428052_981d6b2575_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649311720663/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7599/16967814601_3c692c92f0_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649311720663/"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8695/16942803636_cda573fa98_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649311720663/"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8702/16967427462_5bcd485a8d_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649311720663/"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8702/16762115227_ed51073047_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649311720663/"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8747/16781063798_86cfa296b7_c.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649311720663/">Few more photos in Flickr</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Revelate Designs Bikepacking Gear]]></title>
    <link href="http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2014/11/17/Revelate-Designs-Bikepacking-Gear/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-17T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2014/11/17/Revelate-Designs-Bikepacking-Gear</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When purchasing a fatbike roughly two and a half years ago, one of the goals was to build a rig that could easily be used for mixed terrain bikepacking, year around. Any mountain bike is a great platform already for such endeavors (such as <a href="https://vimeo.com/32149186">bikerafting up and down a river</a>), but the simplicity of a solid, non-suspended frame helps to tackle a heavy payload, and fat tires give a clear edge on varied terrain.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157648916746649/"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5602/15624543189_d8ac6c3256_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Picking components for my <a href="http://fatbackbikes.com">Fatback</a> build, I ran across bike bags from <a href="http://www.revelatedesigns.com">Revelate Designs</a>, a company that specializes in bikepacking gear. <a href="http://speedwaycyclesak.com">Speedway Cycles</a>, through which my order was fulfilled, had a custom-sized frame bag for my 22" frame, and so with the bike build, arrived also a frame bag. While I was first contemplating whether I should only use the bag when going out on a trip, I strapped it on once the bike was finished, and by the date it has not left the frame, even for a day. I never liked wearing a backpack (even those small water bladder bags) while cycling, and it was a revelation to realize that with a frame bag, the days of carrying one on every ride were over - water, snacks, repair kit, camera and much more would now easily travel inside the triangle.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157648916746649/"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5602/15786694276_7dbe737167_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157648916746649/"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5607/15624543419_25c60f08b1_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Couple of months later, while letting go of my full suspension bike which had been slipping into oblivion, I looked into putting some of that cash back to cycling, and got the <a href="https://www.revelatedesigns.com/index.cfm/store.catalog/Seat-Bags/Viscacha">Viscacha</a> seat bag and a <a href="https://www.revelatedesigns.com/index.cfm/store.catalog/Cockpit/Gas-Tank">Gas Tank</a>. Seat bag allowed loading a lot more gear on the bike, and lose the backpack also on overnighters. I continued to strap a dry bag (<a href="http://leftbound.com/stories/Medvasto-Bikerafting/">or a rolled up packraft</a>) on the handlebar, while the gas tank offered convenient access to small items needed frequently. This worked nicely well into 2013, when Revelate Designs started to develop a <a href="https://www.revelatedesigns.com/index.cfm/store.catalog/Handle-Bar/Harnesshandlebarharnesssling">new harness</a> for carrying bulky items more securely on the handle bar. Released and in stock around May, I grabbed one, completing the set.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157648916746649/"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8542/15190912153_fe0094dc2f_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157648916746649/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7471/15786694676_1edcd6d9db_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157648916746649/"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8124/15625178677_acac46fb72_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Frame bag has aged well, showing no signs of fatigue, with all straps and seams intact. There is minor wear on the seal of the water resistant zipper, with a thin strip having peeled off in use. Typical for such zippers under high stress, I am not alarmed by it, nor do I feel it really compromizes the protection from the elements. Gas tank has the same type of seal on the zipper, and so far shows no signs of wear, being under less stress.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157648916746649/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7475/15625179427_7d6d1489f7_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157648916746649/"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8630/15625178957_4875eeff99_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Seat bag has changed a bit since I got mine, now including only one velcro strap around the seat post, and few other minor adjustments. Functionally it&rsquo;s still the same as far as I can see, and comparing the two online, I can spot an essential, though minor, change - the plastic eyelets on the top for a bungee cord. In my version, there is simply 4 cord loops sewn into the seams, and routing a bungee cord through them can easily cut in them in use. I could notice some slight wear on mine early on, and added a piece of cord and some plastic snap hooks to take away the strain - this works well and no further wear is evident so far.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157648916746649/"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8625/15190911483_e40885ddc0_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157648916746649/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7556/15811925162_ce96df0586_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>The new seat bag also sports adjustable position for the seat rail straps, which can be useful for fitting the bag in different bikes (and for example for setback seat posts). Despite the repetitive use (on and off the bike, load and unload) there is no visible wear or tear on the seams, nor do the straps or the fabric show any alarming signs of use. Internal (removable) compression strap is handy, and the roll down closure allows easy volume adjustment (removable plastic bottom sheet provides structural support).</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157648916746649/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7534/15624543209_64e7d51828_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Harness is an interesting piece of gear. When I first received it, it felt a bit overbuilt and heavy, after being used to strap things (mainly a dry bag with gear, or the packraft) directly into the handle bar and it working just fine. Somewhat complex to attach to a busy handle bar, it takes some time to do. However, when tuned up for the bike, and in use, I quickly realized the benefits of the sturdiness, and having shifted cargo up to its load carrying capacity, would not take anything less.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157648916746649/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7496/15624965438_90634b7560_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157648916746649/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7578/15786694806_5b4ff0f3ba_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157648916746649/"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5608/15625178367_f63e45f57b_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Harness comes with two rubber spacer blocks, that allow some distance to the bar, making it easier to route the cables. For me, having two shifters and four cables running from the bar ends, I ended up pulling the blocks loose from the harness (and connecting them with runaway straps to not to loose them accidentally), allowing me to route cables through the cut outs on the front-end of said blocks, resulting to snag free cable routing and the correct alignment of the harness. To prevent the payload from jumping up and down with the harness, a third strap around the head tube, or better, around the fork crown, is used. Some minor abrasion is visible where the harness touches the head tube, but materials used all around are very sturdy and abrasion resistant.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157648916746649/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7564/15786694866_f072eea7a8_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157648916746649/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7529/15625179297_c49cc7fe28_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157648916746649/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7471/15190400304_346e8d8de1_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157648916746649/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7507/15811925152_c3063f5d48_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Latest addition to my set of bike bags is the large, harness compatible <a href="https://www.revelatedesigns.com/index.cfm/store.catalog/Handle-Bar/Pockets">Pocket (large)</a> I got this autumn, and used it first time last weekend. As it clips in to the harness (which ships with the required hardware), it&rsquo;s simple to take into use. I hoped to use it especially for storing camera gear, even DSLR, and other small items, and was happy to confirm it fits a big camera and much more. And as it turned out, it easily converts also into a shoulder bag.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157648916746649/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7543/15808474021_0f62c97e06_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157648916746649/"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5603/15786695506_765b4140bf_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157648916746649/"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8591/15624965908_20d3506c7d_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157648916746649/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7546/15625178857_4839b68182_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>All in all, I am very satisfied with the quality of Revelate Designs bags, and, expecting no failures any time soon, hope to use this set for years to come. If you are after a high quality bikepacking kit, gear from <a href="https://www.revelatedesigns.com/">Revelate Designs</a> is definitely worth a look. As with anything strapped to the frame, beware of the scuff marks (if you care about those, I don&rsquo;t) appearing quickly, stripping off the paint or the anodization - if a concern, you can try protecting the frame with some sort of protective film or tape.</p>

<p>You can order these bags directly from US, and in Europe they are available for example through <a href="http://www.backcountrybiking.co.uk/">Backcountry Biking in UK</a>, <a href="http://fatbikes.at/revelate-designs">Fatbikes.at in Austria</a> and <a href="http://www.singlespeed.nl/catalog/index.php?language=en&amp;osCsid=1080a3a5b2bbca758b5975a6d821ecce">Singlespeed Central in Netherlands</a>. In Finland, you might first want to check what <a href="http://www.shocktherapy.fi">Shock Therapy</a> has in stock. If you want a second opinion on these bags, check out for example <a href="http://www.tramplite.com/2013/03/revelate-bike-bags-review.html">Tramplite&rsquo;s review</a>. Post a comment or a question below if you have some experience with these bags, or need some further details. Current specs are best obtained from <a href="http://www.revelatedesigns.com">Revelate Designs</a> themselves.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Stop Offs]]></title>
    <link href="http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2014/05/09/Stop-Offs/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-09T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2014/05/09/Stop-Offs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Having a business meeting in <a href="http://www.tampere.fi/english/index.html">Tampere</a> yesterday, I dediced to take an opportunity to try and visit some of the outdoor areas nearby. Browsing around, I was contemplating between cycling and packrafting, or combining both, but eventually ended up just bringing the bike, and choosing the destinations accordingly. Out of the available options Kytäjä-Usmi and Evo outdoor areas turned up as favorites, despite the lousy weather forecast for the day.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7459/13958262289_fac10493b0_o.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Starting very early from Espoo, and arrived to one of the parking lots at the <a href="http://kytaja-usmi.fi/">Kytäjä-Usmi outdoor area</a>, nearby lake Usminjärvi. It had been pouring all the way there, but by chance not a drop of rain fell when I unloaded the bike and packed it with basic gear - plan was to have a warm breakfast somewhere on the trail. When browsing the map for a route, sky opened as forecasted and it started raining sleet. Merrily I took a direction towards Kaksoislammit lean-to, following the signposts available along the gravel roads entering the park.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5558/13958261999_585b2222ed_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7407/14121746046_fe48927dbf_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/"><img src="https://farm3.staticflickr.com/2916/14144931625_8b3efd67a0_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>This was my first visit to this area (which is also part of Natura 2000 network), except for the days I&rsquo;ve spent climbing in <a href="http://27crags.com/crags/jaanankallio">Jaanankallio</a> in the past, southwest from the area I was now cycling in. During the two-hour ride, including tracking back my steps to search for a pair of rain gloves I dropped (found them!), I toured east from Piilolammi and Iso Kypärä lakes, and found good sections of varying single track - plus some proper bushwhacking and bike-carrying terrain, but that&rsquo;s bound to happen when you are trying figure out where the good ones are. Rain never stopped, but just the quantity and consistency of sleet was alternating, at times being almost, but not quite, like snow. But great views (small ponds and lakes, bogs, rock cliffs and an old quarry) all around nevertheless.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7342/14145118114_d2d8c51149_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7382/14121746406_d200456a51_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Finishing the ride, I headed towards Tampere, taking a shower (and dipping in the pool) in <a href="http://www.tampere.fi/liikuntajavapaaaika/liikuntajaulkoilu/uimahallit/hervanta.html">Hervanta swimming hall</a>, amidst the handful of senior citizens doing water aerobics and deep water running in the otherwise empty hall. It was great to head to the office refreshed!</p>

<p>After work and an early dinner, it was time to start the journey towards <a href="http://www.outdoors.fi/evo">Evo</a> for an overnighter. Not exactly on the road back home, it&rsquo;s still a reasonable detour diverting from Hämeenlinna and a place I&rsquo;ve had on the to-do list for a while. I knew a group of packrafters, led by Pekka from <a href="http://reppulautta.blogspot.fi/">reppulautta.com</a> were starting their 3-night paddle across the park, and hoped to catch up with them someplace on the trail.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7355/14145118254_edef7dd7fe_o.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Evo, a typical watershed region, is one of the largest continuous forested areas in southern Finland, of which some 47 sq.km is mapped as a hiking area. Splattered with small ponds and lakes and meandering rivers, it&rsquo;s a great spot for packrafting. And due to good network of forest roads, it&rsquo;s also well suited for bikerafting, allowing round trips across the whole area. Not to mention the possibilities for hiking and mountain biking. A good visual overview of the area (including shelters and camp sites) can be found <a href="http://julkaisut.metsa.fi/assets/pdf/lp/Esitteet/evofin.pdf">here</a>.</p>

<p>Arriving quite late, I parked the car on the northeast corner, at lake Iso-Tarus, and loading up the bike again, headed to Nuijamiehenkolo lean-to. Riding on the gravel roads, and sections of single track and few dead ends (while the constant rain kept it fresh), led me there, to find Pekka&rsquo;s group settled for the night in tents. Before settling in myself for the night in the lean-to (no bugs yet = no tent for me), I did a bit of touring around the surrounding lakes and ponds (and sadly some clean-cut areas), finding wide range of trails and single track (while the typical ride-lift-ride-carry-ride-push-ride sequence prevailed).</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7417/14142036702_e8a4e97e47_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Back at the camp, it was time for dinner with an experimental dessert and a good chat around the fire. Exchanging tips and information especially about packrafting destinations, I got some ideas how to use up some of my future weekends inside the rubber dinghy with and/or without a bike.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5441/13958244327_b26328b129_o.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Morning arrived with a very early wake up call and a quick breakfast, before finding a new route back to the car (through some of the trails I missed on the way there) with full day at work ahead back in Espoo.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7344/14144931835_0f94ca0578_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Though relatively superficial, it was great to have an opportunity to visit these two outdoor areas, and once the next time comes, it will be easier to make plans knowing already somewhat what to expect. Not too bad business trip giveaway!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
