<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Nordic Skating | Leftbound]]></title>
  <link href="http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/categories/nordic-skating/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://leftbound.com/leftbound/"/>
  <updated>2018-01-25T01:10:12+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://leftbound.com/leftbound/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Joni Palomäki]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[joni@leftbound.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Early Winter on Skates]]></title>
    <link href="http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2017/01/02/Early-Winter-On-Skates/"/>
    <updated>2017-01-02T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2017/01/02/Early-Winter-On-Skates</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is now the third season running, since adding Nordic Skating (or tour skating) into my winter repertoire of reasons to get out. Settling for a rather unorthodox setup, <a href="http://leftbound.com/blog/2015/01/07/Nordic-Skates-Revamped/">pairing the skates with Dynafit bindings and telemark boots</a>, it&rsquo;s been interesting to learn more about ice and gaining confidence in traveling on lakes and the sea.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/31939778631/in/datetaken/" title="You shall not pass"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/1/606/31939778631_909b2e2280_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="You shall not pass"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>My choice of kit has evolved slightly this year, as I finally added a pair of real skating poles, having resorted to an old pair of telescopic poles, tuned with <a href="https://varuste.net/Exel+Ice+Skater+Tip?_tu=60910">Exel&rsquo;s Ice Skater Tips</a> and weights to better (and safely) serve their new purpose. I originally rigged them up as I had trouble finding long enough poles, but eventually found and switched to a 162 centimeter long <a href="https://www.lundhags.se/Produkter/Nordic-Skating/Ice-Safety/Flash/">Lundhags Flash</a>, conveniently on discount at the end of the season, last spring. While these poles are by far better fit for purpose, I do miss the tripod thread I am not able to fit into the slim handles of said poles.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/31216512584/in/album-72157676751764362/" title="Skating at sunset"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/351/31216512584_881722e1b1_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Skating at sunset"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The skate/binding combo has worked great, without any issues. As I ditched the heel piece early on, to allow free rotation of the skate, the setup is very simple and practically bombproof. Hiking short distances (say, couple of kilometers at max) with these telemark boots is perfectly fine, and I&rsquo;ve only switched to shoes on longer stretches on land. The setup is hence pretty versatile, also providing the much needed support for the lower legs when powered by a small kite - something I plan to test a bit more this winter. At the moment I have no reservations for recommending a similar setup.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/31939786191/in/album-72157676751764362/" title="Setting sun"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/1/582/31939786191_2039bd6a2e_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Setting sun"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Nordic skating can help to fill the potentially grim gap between late autumn and a full blown winter, offering a great way to enjoy the multitude of recently frozen lakes and of course the archipelago. While sea ice was pretty limited last season, this autumn the season kicked off nicely, with potential for very good coverage over the coming months, should winter take and keep roughly its normal course from this point onwards. It would be great to have an opportunity to do a longer tour on the outskirts of the Baltic Sea archipelago, open horizon firmly at sight - fingers crossed!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/31909546662/in/datetaken/" title="Open water near Pentala"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/1/733/31909546662_1b0e3104cc_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Open water near Pentala"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>While I prefer to tour alone or with a friend or two, focusing more on exploration and nature observation rather than mileage or speed, the possibility to join some of the many tours organized by <a href="https://www.skrinnari.fi/skridskonet/foreningen/">Skrinnari</a>, a national tour skating club, is a great asset. As a member of said club, having completed the basic training, one is free to join any of the organized tours, varying in speed and length, and tap into the online resource which offers up-to-date information on ice conditions and also plenty of insight and inspiration for self-organized tours. This season, I&rsquo;ve joined two organized tours - one early on close by and another one further away, in Raasepori.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/31216477844/in/datetaken/" title="Thin ice"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/1/286/31216477844_46534024b6_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Thin ice"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After kicking off the season on December 10, with a 30-kilometer tour at the outskirts of solid ice in the inner arhipelago, I joined a 2-day trip across Espoo and Kirkkonummi archipelago, which my fellow adventurer <a href="https://twitter.com/mtakanen">Marko</a> had plotted on a map. A mix of uncertainty, adversity, achievement and awe, it had all the key elements of a fun and rewarding adventure. Video from the trip is embedded below.</p>

<iframe width="770" height="433" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/PQ1h-nqi8wk" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>The last tour I did before the year end was a bus tour to Raasepori, organized by Skrinnari. Having explored the Västerby region on foot and <a href="http://leftbound.com/blog/2014/05/05/Raseborg-Looksee/">by bike</a> before, the jagged lake uplands on that same area were of great interest. Upon arrival in Tammisaari, the busload of skaters split into few groups, with five of us deciding to go explore the area not previously visited by the club. Starting out with a hike to lake Långträsket, we spent the day circumventing wilderness-like lakes, including Grabbskog Storträsket, following every nook and granny on mostly superb ice.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/32018597406/in/datetaken/" title="Over the ice"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/1/375/32018597406_fdbb1d70a3_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Over the ice"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Spotting animal tracks across snowy patches on lake ice, some were easier to identify than others. Sliding marks were no brainer, though the jesting otter was nowhere to be seen, tracks finishing to an air hole. Weather remaining overcast and foggy, it just added to the experience and the day was a success. Finishing the 40-kilometer tour with a loop around the inner Gennarbyviken bay, weather turned soggy, and we skirted around shallow pools of water to the finish - journey back home begun at sundown.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/31939777011/in/datetaken/" title="The crucifix wall"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/1/273/31939777011_aaef4dae89_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="The crucifix wall"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/32057644805/in/datetaken/" title="Lunch at a lean-to"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/1/494/32057644805_f217050d8d_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Lunch at a lean-to"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/31682784180/in/datetaken/" title="Behind the branches"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/1/463/31682784180_e3d29c3ac5_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Behind the branches"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s 2017 now, and we finally have a second go on white winter, after <a href="http://leftbound.com/blog/2016/11/17/Six-Days-Of-Awe/">November&rsquo;s bliss</a>, as the new snow just fell last night. Cold front now sweeping over Finland, with temperatures dropping as low as minus twenty degrees celcius even in the south, the Nordic skating season continues strong. See you on ice!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/31909618112/in/album-72157676751764362/" title="Giant&#x27;s stone"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/515/31909618112_6e0fccfd14_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Giant&#x27;s stone"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>&#10095;&#10095; Flickr album (with more photos): <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157676751764362">Early Winter on Skates</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Nordic Skates Revamped]]></title>
    <link href="http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2015/01/07/Nordic-Skates-Revamped/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-07T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2015/01/07/Nordic-Skates-Revamped</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve never been much of an ice skater, but used to roller skate years ago quite a bit, and memories from childhood mostly, skating with flimsy leather skates, have effectively kept me off the ice rinks ever since. Few years ago I did had to jump back on it, to enjoy this dreaded sport with my daughter. Back on ice, but not thrilled about it, I thought Nordic skating could be fun. But few short tests with different boots, such as ones for cross-country skiing and ice climbing, left me wanting for more support. Having a size 46 foot, but narrow and loose ankles is not an optimal combination for a sport that demands control and strength on lower legs, and well-fitting, supporting shoes have been hard to come by.</p>

<p>I had played around with an idea to use my telemark boots for ultimate control, but having switched from the old norm to NTN, could not make myself to invest into another pair of Rottefella Freeride/Freedom&rsquo;s just to try if it would work, and generic bindings did not seem like a good fit. I was also concerned if the mere weight of the plastic boots would be an issue for skating. Last winter I read about some of the amazing tours <a href="http://thingstolucat.com/aniak-to-dillingham/">Luc Mehl had done in Alaska</a>, and noticed he was using his Dynafit boots and bindings also with skates. Come this winter, encouraged, I decided I would try to work something out, and finding a great deal on pair of <a href="http://www.seatosummit.se/Laangfaerdsskridskor.htm">Skyllermarks</a> Möja skate/binding combo at <a href="http://www.bearwater.fi/">Bear &amp; Water</a>, I was ready for a trial when the first snow fell.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649741335678/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7555/16212907495_78639f18a0_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Per recommendation from Bear &amp; Water, I got myself relatively long, 53 cm, skates. Möja binding is a good fit for the old norm telemark boots, but can be adjusted to work with any boot with some kind of lip up front, or to a normal hiking boot with additional arch on top of the toe piece. Putting them on, front of the boot is slid under the toe piece and heel is locked in place on the heel cup with strap. I tested this setup for the first time on my old pair of Garmont Prophets NTNs, on the local outdoor ice rink.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649741335678/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7478/16187041116_c2a51aba3e_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>While binding worked in principle, solid plastic boot with upwards arching sole put quite a lot of stress on the toe piece (which bent slightly), made of some sort of plastic composite, and skating few kilometers around the rink I could notice the strap did not perfectly hold the heel in place, allowing boot to shift lightly. Once it loosened up until the skate came off - not a pleasant thing to happen at speed, I tell you that. Instead of running the strap over the boot, I also tried to route it through the walk/ski locking mechanism on the back of the boot. Better, but heel still not stay perfectly in place and left me wondering if the skate could again come off too easily, due to the small front lip on NTN boots (as opposed to more generous duckbills on the old norm boots).</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649741335678/"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8563/16027088157_15cd8fc5b2_z.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>As I was midst replacing my telemark boots with slimmer model (Prophets were always a bit too wide for me, but since I got them super cheap few years back, I stuck with them merrily until this winter), Garmonts were soon gone, and my new boots from Scarpa, <a href="http://www.scarpa.com/terminator-x">Terminator X</a>, sported Dynafit inserts. I looked at the different types and versions of Dynafit compatible bindings, and put up a want-to-buy add on <a href="http://relaa.com">Relaa.com</a> marketplace, for a pair of any Dynafit toe pieces. Dynafit-compatible bindings are quite common, and relatively easy to find also second hand. Heel pieces not required, you might want to optimize the cost, and get just the toe pieces from <a href="http://www.skimo.co">The Ski Mountaineering Company</a>. Not many stores sell those separately, and Skimo has a good range of models to choose from.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649741335678/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7470/15590505064_1c6b87588e_z.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>The bindings I have are <a href="http://www.dynafit.com/en/tlt-speed-turn.html">Dynafit Speed Turn</a>, a classic entry-level model, perfectly fit for this purpose. All Dynafit bindings are step-in and come with release mechanism which could turn out to be a knee-saver and the rest, such as the crampon clip, is irrelevant. Speed Turn weighs 157 grams each, and while the race versions are even lighter, down to 78 grams each, the difference is negligible considering the total weight with boots somewhere around 1 - 1.5 kg each.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649741335678/"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8662/16026809929_a7640b3a70_z.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Speed Turn hole pattern is almost a perfect fit to Skyllermarks rail - a touch of file on the aluminum finished the job, and it was easy to attach the bindings securely on the exact spot I wanted. Speed Turn has actually five holes on the base plate, the fifth one being up front under the lever, right in the middle. Obviously with T-shaped skate it&rsquo;s not possible to utilize this, but four is plenty in my opinion.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649741335678/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7543/16027088017_662253e415_z.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>This week the sea ice had reached ample thickness to extend my testing outside of the ice rink, and on Monday I had the first run on the surprisingly smooth ice on my backdoor bay in Kivenlahti. While Dynafit, made for ski alpinism, allows free rotation around the pins, I hadn&rsquo;t really made up my mind whether I prefer the heel free or locked down - I kept on the Möja heel cups to easily lock it down. Come Tuesday and Boxing day, I headed out again, this time with <a href="https://twitter.com/mtakanen/">Marko</a>, on a full moon to sunrise tour around Espoonlahti. As we carried day trip gear on our backs, it was good to test the balance when keeping the heels free, and I had absolutely no issues with it. After the trip I removed the heel cups, to be carried as a spare with Möja toe piece, should the Dynafit ever fail on a tour.</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="fi"><p>Amazing skating tour from moonset to sunrise w/ <a href="https://twitter.com/j_palomaki">@j_palomaki</a>. <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/nordicskating?src=hash">#nordicskating</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/retkiluistelu?src=hash">#retkiluistelu</a> <a href="http://t.co/5v5f1BAk5T">pic.twitter.com/5v5f1BAk5T</a></p>&mdash; Marko E. Takanen (@mtakanen) <a href="https://twitter.com/mtakanen/status/552405968668356608">6. tammikuuta 2015</a></blockquote>


<p> <script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The tour we did extended until and around the open water line at Pentala. With relatively smooth ice and not much wind it was a stunning cruise first with full moon on our backs, and then enjoying a cup of coffee on an island, backlit by rising sun on the horizon. It was also an educational one, negotiating the route around an island with varying quality and thickness of ice, learning to probe and analyze. Few times we had to walk ashore to avoid an inevitable plunge. Dynafit allows quick in and out, and telemark boots are plenty comfortable to hike some distances.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649741335678/"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8628/16025402028_dcc4f7259b_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649741335678/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7565/16026810249_0a5ef11c05_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649741335678/"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8572/15590504704_4d96141ee9_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649741335678/"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8638/16025402108_d3f9883b8d_z.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Verdict on this revamped setup is so far very positive. Added support and control is enough reason for me, and boots like this are toasty and more or less waterproofed for added comfort on the go. For longer tours the removable inner boots are handy, just stash them in your sleeping bag overnight. Dynafit bindings are light, simple and robust, proven many times over on demanding ski tours around the globe.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649741335678/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7580/16212907575_4f7f5c6494_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>The weight of the plastic boot will certainly take an extra toll on your thighs and buttocks, but at the same time will reduce fatigue on lower leg. It&rsquo;s too early to make a solid statement, but it just might balance out. Further mileage will tell - looking forward to it! Today I played with my trainer kite on skates, and will be trying out the large one if the conditions hold - beefy boots will surely help also in that.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157649741335678/"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8671/16025401578_9ab6219bc9_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>In addition to this combination, similar concept could easily be applied to a 75mm telemark boot and the Skyllermarks bindings or similar. Or if you prefer your heels free, classic Rottefella Super Telemark or some other &ldquo;rat-trap&rdquo;, 3-pin binding should work well.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
