<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Traveling | Leftbound]]></title>
  <link href="http://leftbound.com/blog/categories/traveling/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://leftbound.com/"/>
  <updated>2020-01-09T22:00:44+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://leftbound.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Joni Palomäki]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[joni@leftbound.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Järvsö - 3700 dm.ö.h]]></title>
    <link href="http://leftbound.com/blog/Jarvso-3700-Dmoh/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-03T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://leftbound.com/blog/Jarvso-3700-Dmoh</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For the last three winters in a row, our family&rsquo;s winter vacation (school&rsquo;s out for week 8) has taken us to <a href="http://www.are360.com/en/">Åre</a>, in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/J%C3%A4mtland_County">Jämtland</a>. Main reason we have been lately opting to go to Sweden, instead of heading up north in Finland, is the ease of travel, requiring lot less driving. Each time we&rsquo;ve driven there, a small town called Järvsö has been passed, just before Ljusdal, and each time we&rsquo;ve wondered out loud, what kind of resort that would be.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/28741122140/in/album-72157665251303531/" title="Untitled"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/9/8445/28741122140_3f8520cf75_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Untitled"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Come this spring, we recalled Järvsö and after checking it online and learning there was a new ski-in/ski-out hotel, <a href="http://www.bergshotellet.se">Bergshotellet</a>, built during 2015 and now open for the first season - we quickly deciced to skip Åre this year, and go finally check this place out. This year we had also other commitments for the vacation days, so similar to our <a href="http://leftbound.com/blog/2016/02/02/Hemavan-On-Skis/">Hemavan trip</a> at the end of the year, we decided three full skiing days would do. A familiar route, we chose again to cross the Baltic Sea on <a href="http://www.tallinksilja.fi/">Tallink Silja</a> ferries, this time Silja Symphony, which had a nice new sushi restaurant, Sushi &amp; Co. There are always shows on these boats, typically 2-3 during the evening (aerobatics, music, dancing and whatnot), but this time there was a bonus gig, as one of the coveted pop artists in Finland at the moment, <a href="http://petoonirti.com">Antti Tuisku</a>, was starting a two-week tour on the boat, and we got to see the first one. Not my kind of music, I must say, but live performances are always fun to watch, with the rest of the crowd.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/28922326262/in/album-72157665251303531/" title="Untitled"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/9/8416/28922326262_ec20e42b82_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Untitled"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/28922326902/in/album-72157665251303531/" title="Untitled"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/9/8409/28922326902_d4f0cf9582_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Untitled"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Arriving to Stockholm next morning and only about 320 kilometers to drive to Järvsö, we spent few ours roaming the city, and started towards Järvsö early afternoon. We quickly arrived to Tönnebro on E4 and diverted inlands towards Ljusdal, reaching our destination only after four hours of driving.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/28994585326/in/album-72157665251303531/" title="Untitled"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/9/8041/28994585326_804cf17b1b_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Untitled"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Arriving at the hotel late in the evening, we had a dinner at the <a href="http://www.bergshotellet.se/bergskrogen">Bergskrogen</a>, to not have to go searching for a restaurant downtown. And as the restaurant turned out to be very good, we dined there again (they also have a great lunch buffé), and naturally had breakfast there every morning. Everything brand new, lots of wood was used as building material, and for decoration and furniture. Following a kind of eco-friendly approach, the restaurant for example sources much of the incredients locally, makes their own bread, and so on. It was a fantastic place to stay in, must say!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/29027416795/in/album-72157665251303531/" title="Untitled"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/9/8107/29027416795_ac7146dfd7_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Untitled"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>A ski-in/ski-out hotel, we had a kids slope, and a platter lift, just in front of the hotel, with a conveyor-belt style skilift also for the small sledding hill on the side (with small snow scoots to borrow at the hotel). And a nice movable stall serving fresh crepés and beverages.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/29027387495/in/album-72157665251303531/" title="Untitled"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/9/8524/29027387495_37a18102b0_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Untitled"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a href="http://jarvso.se">Järvsö</a> ski resort has two sides - south side, where the hotel is at, and north, where majority of the slopes are. As the resort is not very big, all slopes are accessible from either side, connected on the top, at 3700 decimeters over the sea, as they playfully state on the top lift station. Resort puts a lot of effort into maintaining the piste, and all the slopes are prepared each day, as they close at 16:30 (except on Tuesday and Thursday, when there&rsquo;s night skiing on the north side from 18:00 to 20:30). During our stay, the slopes were all in excellent condition, and while there is no real off piste to speak of (some forest trails and bike paths to run, but there wasn&rsquo;t that much snow and terrain is thick and rocky), we had a blast skiing in the sun for all three days. Especially the slopes number 12, 13 and 15 were our favorites, as well as number 3 on the south side.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/28741124530/in/album-72157665251303531/" title="Untitled"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/9/8770/28741124530_ebfa429a8b_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Untitled"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/28741123270/in/album-72157665251303531/" title="Untitled"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/9/8222/28741123270_13d46737da_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Untitled"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>In the area, just behind the hotel, there is also a zoo, <a href="http://www.jarvzoo.se">Järvzoo</a>. In there, built on the slopes just next to the piste, a range of Nordic animals can be viewed in their natural environment (considering it&rsquo;s still a zoo). A wooden walkway leads through it (accessible also by wheelchair), forming a loop roughly 3 kilometers in length. While the zoo is open only until 15:00 during winter season, one can enter just before that, and spend as long as needed inside - this is also what we did, as we first had a day&rsquo;s worth of skiing bagged, and then entered the zoo just before closing time.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/28410008263/in/album-72157665251303531/" title="Untitled"><img src="https://c8.staticflickr.com/9/8318/28410008263_d87693ebf4_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Untitled"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I hoped to get a glimpse of were wolves, wolverines and lynxes, and got plenty of good views of all but the last, as lynxes could not be found in the plain daylight. I recommend bringing binoculars, as the encloses are relatively large (which is good), so you will get better views with them. I tried to take a few photos through my Leica Ultravid 8X25 binoculars, but could not really get them sharp, handheld and not attached together in any way.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/28922346912/in/album-72157665251303531/" title="Untitled"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8385/28922346912_348f0ff1e2_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Untitled"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>While it was nice to see those animals live, especially wolves which I followed for a long time, the really nice surprise came in the evening. It was thursday, so the north side had the night skiing ongoing. Rather than taking the free bus transfer to the other side, I opted to skin up in the dark, and ski a few laps on the illuminated slopes on the other side, before skiing back down to the hotel from the top, equipped with a headlamp.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/28951317851/in/album-72157665251303531/" title="Untitled"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/9/8354/28951317851_1eaaccfd60_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Untitled"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Skinning up, I could listen the owls calling in the dark - there were several types of owls in the zoo, I think what I heard was the long-eared owl. Then, stopping to view the surroundings under the full moon, I saw a wolf emerging from the woods behind and downhill of me, and lope across the piste, to disappear into the woods again. This was the first time I&rsquo;ve seen a wolf run free, and though I had just been viewing a pack of them inside the zoo, it was a cool bonus for the evening&rsquo;s little ski tour!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/28922353112/in/album-72157665251303531/" title="Untitled"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8112/28922353112_54f67a8f0e_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Untitled"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>On the morning of departure, I used the last opportunity to get some more mileage on skins, and did another &lsquo;topptur&rsquo; after breakfast, skinning up the long meandering blue piste and across the forest, to the top, for the very last run. During our stay I had only seen few other people on telemark skis, and now me ski touring there on such gear in bright daylight triggered a few smiles and thumbs up on the way up. A perfect ending for a nice vacation, glad we chose Järvsö as our destination, let&rsquo;s see if we&rsquo;ll make another visit (or a stop) here sometime. I can warmly recommend this resort, and the hotel, especially if you travel with kids, even very small ones. Outside the Bergskrogen, there&rsquo;re several other good restaurants to go to - check especially the cozy <a href="http://www.condis.se">Condis Bar &amp; Kök</a>. And lots of cottages as well! Note though that Järvsö is often fully booked, also why the new hotel was welcomed to the area, so book on time.</p>

<p>&#10095;&#10095; Flickr album (with more photos): <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/albums/72157665251303531">Järvsö - 3700 dm.ö.h</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hemavan on Skis]]></title>
    <link href="http://leftbound.com/blog/Hemavan-On-Skis/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-02T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://leftbound.com/blog/Hemavan-On-Skis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With Christmas vacations typically spent around southern Ostrobothnia, from where our families are, many times we&rsquo;ve been discussing to free up a few days around Christmas and/or New Year and travel across kvarken to ski in the Swedish fells. While typically we dash through bunch of friends and relatives during those days, which is great but also hectic and consuming, we welcomed a late reservation through booking.com into <a href="http://www.hemavansfjallcenter.se">Hemavans Fjällcenter</a>, a <a href="https://www.svenskaturistforeningen.se">Svenska Turistföreningen (STF)</a> facility. Once confirmed, we booked the ferry across the kvarken, from Vaasa to Umeå, nowadays operated by <a href="http://www.wasaline.com/en/">Wasaline</a>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/28742496960/in/photostream/" title="On the ferry to Umeå"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8096/28742496960_113669dc70_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1536" alt="On the ferry to Umeå"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Come Boxing Day, we boarded the ferry in Vaasa, with heavy winds (around 20 meters per second) pounding the harbor. Needless to say the journey across was on rough seas, but as the distance is quite short, it took only about four hours, until we docked in Umeå.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/28742496960/in/dateposted/" title="On the ferry to Umeå"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8096/28742496960_113669dc70_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1536" alt="On the ferry to Umeå"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Although the distance between Umeå and Hemavan is only about 380 kilometers, the road conditions were quite tough on our trip, with much of it being on iced up roads, which slowed us down a bit. With friction tires under the car, I didn&rsquo;t want to push it, but rather arrive a bit later, but without incidents, to Hemavan. We had no rush as the skiing would only start the next day.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/28742498520/in/photostream/" title="Lift to the high zone"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8792/28742498520_bc508b9856_k.jpg" width="1536" height="2048" alt="Lift to the high zone"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Hemavan Fjällcenter is a cozy guesthouse-like hotel/hostel, with several one-floor buildings with rooms and facilities. In addition to the hotel room we stayed in, there&rsquo;s also an option for room with just beds and a faucet - toilets and showers, and kitchen, would then be shared. We originally had booked the latter option, but closer to the trip, upgraded to a hotel room with a very small fee. We ended up staying in building Renen, opposite the main building, which had been just refurbished. The only thing we would have liked to have was a dryer and a locker for skis, to stash the wet gear after the day - now we just had to fill up the bathroom. Breakfast was served in the main building and was top notch - same goes for the dinner buffé we had on our arrival night. Sadly that was the only time we could enjoy it, as it did not run during the weekdays, at this time of the year.</p>

<p>Fjällcenter, as it turned out, is THE place for people riding snowmobiles. Tracks start at the backdoor, and every morning there were tens and tens of snowmobiles revving the engines at the yard and hitting the extensive trail network around Hemavan-Tärnaby region. Skiers, although that week in minority, have it almost as good, with only a short walk from the Fjällcenter to the nearest lift station (Centrumliften) - no car was needed during our stay to get in and out of the slopes.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/28742500360/in/photostream/" title="Mom and dad"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8611/28742500360_dbc1e77282_k.jpg" width="1536" height="2048" alt="Mom and dad"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>We got really lucky with the weather, despite the high winds preceding. There had been a good dump of snow couple of days before, and while during our first day the high zone (lifts) was closed due to wind, the lower zone offered superb skiing, on and off piste, with few of the closed (but roughly prepared before the snow fall) piste having a knee plus deep powder to plow all day. No crowd meant no queuing for the lifts, and virgin powder was easily found until day&rsquo;s end, taking new lines each round.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/28408476744/in/photostream/" title="Powder!"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8506/28408476744_4619d44654_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1536" alt="Powder!"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Next day the wind had calmed down up in the fells, and the high zone lifts were opened. As the high zone had been closed since the snow fall, snow was again untouched and with vast plateau above the treeline to zigzag, we did not run out of powder that day either. My daughter hadn&rsquo;t really skied off piste (or powder) before this trip, but now she was going at it second day in a row, not wanting to cross the prepared piste, I think she&rsquo;s hooked for good!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/28742499920/in/photostream/" title="Soft terrain ahead"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8165/28742499920_d64e9afcaf_k.jpg" width="1536" height="2048" alt="Soft terrain ahead"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Third day, and our last day offered more of the same, but the lower zone now prepared all across, we stayed most on the high zone, finding remaining patches of untouched snow, which was still soft at the treeline and below, while it had started to pack and harden higher up. From above the treeline, traversing to skiers right, there&rsquo;s very good skiing in the woods, as I learned from a local I met in the lift - snow was fluffy and plentiful also there. I had a friend who came over to Hemavan on our last day, so we had few runs together and few folköl&rsquo;s in the neat new <a href="http://www2.hemavantarnaby.se/sv/mat-dryck/a1043743/bj%C3%B6rk-topprestaurang-fj%C3%A4llbar/detaljer?filter=c%3D12096">Björk</a> restaurant, up on the fell (top of the Sollkatsliften).</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/29028796285/in/photostream/" title="Sun down low"><img src="https://c6.staticflickr.com/9/8038/29028796285_8835c2cc77_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Sun down low"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After three great days of skiing, our legs were toast, so a break from skiing was due. This time, it had also come time to end our short vacation and head back to Umeå and across the, again stormy, seas back to Finland, to celebrate New Year.</p>

<p><a href="http://hemavantarnaby.se/oppettider-och-pistkarta-hemavans-skidsystem/">Hemavan</a> resort did not leave much to desire, it was pretty much what we expected and wanted - Mellow slopes with easy access off piste and good skiing in general. The town, if you can call it that, is very small, a cluster of houses with a grocery store and few restaurants, some of which were surprisingly closed during our stay, and opening up only for the New Year. The days between Christmas and New Year are low key, so expect no crowd - great! Same goes for the week 8 (protip!), the winter vacation week at schools in southern Finland.</p>

<p>One of the additional bonuses, though only available from February onwards, is the very affordable heli-skiing, taking skiers to the nearby fells for very a reasonable fee. The booking is also made easy and practical. You call to a number, stating when you are in the area and available (non-binding), and you will be notified when a group is formed and conditions allow to fly, typically the previous day. As we all liked the place a lot, we&rsquo;ll certainly be back, and hopefully then will be able to give a try that heli-skiing as well!</p>

<p>Sometimes it&rsquo;s good to leave the camera behind and simply enjoy the views, rather than trying to make digital copies of them. This trip was one of such for me, and I barely pulled out the camera to grab a photo. Photos featured in this post are hence mostly from my daughter&rsquo;s iPhone.</p>

<p>&#10095;&#10095; Flickr album: <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/albums/72157671376931870">Hemavan on Skis</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Scratching Iceland]]></title>
    <link href="http://leftbound.com/blog/Scratching-Iceland/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-07T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://leftbound.com/blog/Scratching-Iceland</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>S t u n n e d . And I barely touched the surface.</p>

<p>I was traveling for work last week in this wonderland. Not the most typical business destination, I was stoked to have an opportunity to visit a country that has been on my to-do list for quite some time. The <a href="http://www.roughguides.com/shop/rough-guide-iceland/book/">Rough Guide</a> standing idle on the bookshelf (bought several years ago in anticipation of a trip that never happened) finally came handy.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157641624053973/"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3790/12801162244_d91f308e63_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Occupied with work, I spent majority of the time in or near <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reykjavik">Reykjavík</a>, world&rsquo;s northernmost capital, which struck me as a nice small and cozy hang around town with vivid nightlife, excellent cuisine and plenty of friendly locals. With very good restaurants (and a selection of fish, langoustine and lamb with good amount of locally produced, organic ingredients) and gigs, museums and exhibitions around the town, evenings flew by.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157641624053973/"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7440/12801160984_51af426a10_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Surrounded by the sea, mountains and varied terrain with rivers and lakes, long list of activities is just around the corner, easily accessible for anyone either through one of the tour operators or simply self guided, with boats, busses, rental cars and bicycles. With limited time to spare, I participated one organized tour (Golden Circle), took a boat out to watch whales and dolphins, and spent a day driving along the south coast in a rental car, to get out of the the town few times. The North Atlantic Ocean was showing off throughout the week, and with summer being somewhat delayed I got a healthy dose of varied icelandic weather - mostly rain (or overcast) and wind, with temperatures around 5 - 10 degrees celsius. But also few brief moments in the sun and milder temps.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157641624053973/"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3704/12801164254_bcdaffac92_o.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Iceland is a photographic heaven, so it&rsquo;s good to stock up with memory cards and extra batteries. I shoot with Canon 6D now and was glad to have such a well-sealed body - paired with a sealed EF 17-40mm f/4L (and UV filter) it was less of a worry to use in marginal conditions. My other 2 lenses (EF 135mm f/2L and EF 50mm f/1.4 USM) are not sealed, but was using especially the 135 mm quite a lot also in light rain (with UV filter and the hood on most of the time) with no issues at all.</p>

<hr />

<p>Few personal recommendations for a Reykjavík-based visit:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://grapevine.is/Home/"><strong>The Reykjavík Grapevine</strong></a> - grab one of these free magazines from a stand (or browse as PDF online) for your weekly whereabouts.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.icelandexcursions.is/"><strong>Iceland Excursions</strong></a> - inexpensive airport transfer (around 24 eur for a return ticket), all the way to your hotel. They also offer a wide array of tours from Reykjavík (I did the crowded <a href="http://www.icelandexcursions.is/tour/day_tours/AH12_the_golden_circle_classic/Iceland.is">Golden Circle</a> with them), discounted booking online.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.facebook.com/pages/Caf%C3%A9-Rosenberg/235965816459522?fref=ts"><strong>Café Rosenberg</strong></a> - live music through the week, venues are listed on the blackboard at the back of the stage (and promoted in Facebook).</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.facebook.com/pages/12-T%C3%B3nar/28436755255"><strong>12 Tónar</strong></a> - your friendly 2-floor record store. Put on the headphones and sample local music, seated in a sofa sipping fresh coffee on the house. Leave the store with at least 2 albums, to get your 24% back at the airport.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.whalewatching.is/"><strong>Elding - Adventure at Sea</strong></a> - environmentally certified, family-owned tour operator that operates from Reykjavik&rsquo;s old harbour.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Restaurants</strong> - <a href="http://www.fishandchips.is/">Fish &amp; Chips</a> (on steroids), <a href="http://saegreifinn.is/">Saegreifinn</a> (lobster (langoustine) soup and fish skewers), <a href="http://www.sjavargrillid.com/">Sjavargrillid</a>, <a href="http://www.grillmarkadurinn.is/">Grillmarkadurinn</a>, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/B%C3%A6jarins_Beztu_Pylsur">Baejarins beztu</a> (line up for best hot dogs in town), <a href="http://fiskmarkadurinn.is/english/index.php">Fiskmarkadurinn</a> and <a href="http://www.textil.is/ENGLISH/">Café Loki</a> (for icelandic flatbread and sweet rye bread with toppings from local fish to sheep head jelly and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/H%C3%A1karl">hákarl</a> (maybe with a shot of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brenniv%C3%ADn">brennivín</a>, although the taste is not as bad as the stingy smell of ammonia), just to name a few. <a href="http://www.kruathai.is/homeen.html">Krua Thai</a> in the old harbour also deserves to be flagged for inexpensive but extremely tasty thai dishes.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.visitreykjavik.is/desktopdefault.aspx/tabid-176/392_read-1546"><strong>Kolaportið flea market</strong></a> - if you happen to be in town during weekend, local goodies and handicraft.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.maritimemuseum.is/english/home/"><strong>Víkin Maritime Museum</strong></a> - an interesting view to the fishermen&rsquo;s life back in the days, and the coastal culture. Changing exhibitions include a walk through on old coast guard vessel Óðinn, which also played a role in the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cod_Wars">Cod Wars</a>.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.reykjavik.is/desktopdefault.aspx/tabid-3697/6079_view-1546/"><strong>Laugardalslaug</strong></a> - perhaps a more local choice (compared to milky waters of <a href="http://www.bluelagoon.com/">Blue Lagoon</a>) for a swim, there are few other similar pools in the town as well (and it costs next to nothing).</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hallgr%C3%ADmskirkja"><strong>Hallgrímskirkja</strong></a> - splendid view over the town from the tower (ticket is couple of euros only).</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/J%C3%B6kuls%C3%A1rl%C3%B3n"><strong>Jökulsárlón</strong></a> - the magical lagoon is a spectacular sight. I drove 800 km in a day to include this in my tour, and it was definitely worth it (and there&rsquo;s plenty of things to see on the way). Passing forward a good advice I got, take a Zodiac (rubber boat) ride in the lagoon, as opposed to one of the larger amphibious vessels (1 hour trip was around 40 eur). Or bring a packraft like I did not, it would get you even closer to the massive icebergs and the 300 meters of cold blue water underneath you. And watch for those seals that occasionally roam from the river to lagoon.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Car rentals</strong> - plenty of options, prices are reasonable (except for the <a href="http://www.isak.is/">Super Jeeps</a>). Normal car is fine on the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Route_1_(Iceland">ring road</a>) (and on some smaller sand roads departing from it), but further exploration requires a four wheel drive (and caution, you wouldn&rsquo;t be the first ending up upside down, on the side of the road or in the river). Windscreen insurance is recommended (inexpensive, but there&rsquo;s a lot of loose rock all around, ring road included), as well as the Super CDW to ensure relaxed driving all around.</p></li>
</ul>


<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157641624053973/"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3818/12800847523_67c6338817_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>This first visit definitely left me wanting for more, and I am already making initial plans for the next visit, whenever I get a change to stay a bit longer, and focus purely on the great outdoors. Climbing, cycling and packrafting would definitely be on the menu (the meandering glacial rivers on the south coast alone are worth a new trip with a packraft), perhaps in a form of some kind of a road trip around the whole island.</p>

<p>For views and scenes around Reykjavík and southwest/east of Iceland, browse the Flickr set below (switch to full screen mode). If you use Spotify, hit the play button for some background tunes from Rökkurró. And then go book a trip!</p>

<iframe allowtransparency="true" frameborder="0" height="80" src="https://embed.spotify.com/?uri=spotify:track:0yiwg6T9AUo7AXGUHg2EWL" width="300"></iframe>




<iframe src="http://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/12800844503/in/set-72157641624053973/player/" width="640" height="427" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen oallowfullscreen msallowfullscreen></iframe>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Menorca]]></title>
    <link href="http://leftbound.com/blog/Menorca/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-03T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://leftbound.com/blog/Menorca</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Looking for a destination for a trip with the family into someplace warm and sunny, we ran across an island I never had paid attention to earlier - <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minorca">Menorca</a>. Menorca is one of the Balearic Islands (including also Mallorca, Ibiza and Formentera), and among the four perhaps the most pristine and peaceful (with majority of visitors coming from Spain). We booked the trip only couple of weeks prior to departure, and ended up on the western side of the island, near the city of Ciutadella.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157641626299714/"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3739/12800838523_8fc848911b_o.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Menorca is quite small, around 50 km long, 15-20 km wide. It has several archeological sites, and around the island there&rsquo;s an old rugged pathway (almost 190 km in length), <a href="http://www.elcamidecavalls.cat/cami/">Cami De Cavalls</a>, which provides opportunities for hiking, horse riding and mountain biking, and access to varying terrain and many of the coves especially on the south side of the island, unreachable by car.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157641626299714/"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2877/12800903973_2ae58ac349_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>The week was obviously filled with lot of swimming in the Balearic Sea and exploring the island by foot, bike and car (and feasting on Spanish cousine), but this time I also had a new tool for island exploration, the packraft.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157641626299714/"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7296/12800904213_d9929fe7d8_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>While we toured around the island, I carried the raft with me at all times we were near the sea, and used the various opportunities to paddle out. In some of the popular beaches nearby towns with road access there were also rental kayaks available (and the usual pedalboats), but we mostly headed to more distant coves, with 30-60 minutes approach hikes from the end of the road. Leaving the sandy beaches behind, I could paddle pretty much in solitude - pushing through waves, gliding underneath limestone cliffs rising from the sea,  snorkeling and exploring caves.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157641626299714/"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7405/12801218764_98120c6f5d_o.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157641626299714/"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7298/12800905123_a1e8c1f550_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157641626299714/"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7332/12800795955_0c5271cd23_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>One day I met 2 kayakers fully geared up who were on a tour around the island, and while packraft would hardly be the best choice for such a long trip, smaller scale tours along the coastline would be very feasible, similar to what <a href="http://gettingnowhere.net/2012/01/lets-go-to-the-canary-islands/">Ania and Mat did in Canary Islands</a>.</p>

<p>During the week I also used the opportunity to practice wet exit and entry, finding out the tipping point of a loaded and empty raft and just playing around in the warm sea, pleasant unlike in the muddy, murky rivers back at home.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157641626299714/"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7310/12801219154_00e41e279c_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>I had planned to rent a mountain bike for couple of days, to do few longer rides along the Cami, but eventually could not find time for anything more than exploring the trails around the south-east corner of the island for few hours on the last day. The bike I got was slightly too small for me, and hardly up for the task on technical rocky trails (and I ran it almost with flat tires due to slow leakage on the rear and not being able to fix it as the shop gave me a broken pump with the bike), but for a short trip it was fine. With a bit more capable bike, and couple of days to spare, it would be a nice ride around the whole island.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157641626299714/"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2811/12801218044_f0dd12f273_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157641626299714/"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7412/12801217874_14016819e8_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157641626299714/"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7294/12800782565_5f1371b418_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157641626299714/"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2834/12800794905_3ac4480081_o.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
