<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Photography | Leftbound]]></title>
  <link href="http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/categories/photography/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://leftbound.com/leftbound/"/>
  <updated>2018-01-25T00:28:03+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://leftbound.com/leftbound/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Joni Palomäki]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[joni@leftbound.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[MYOG - Monopod Pole]]></title>
    <link href="http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2017/01/11/MYOG-Monopod-Pole/"/>
    <updated>2017-01-11T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2017/01/11/MYOG-Monopod-Pole</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I don&rsquo;t own a real, full-size, tripod and actually haven&rsquo;t had one since I bought my first digital camera, back in 2001. I have however had a small selection of small tripods to carry around, when I need to rest the camera on something more sophisticated than a fence, tree branch or say, a pile of snow and a glove. Of those portables, Gorillapod has proven to be most versatile, though I&rsquo;ve had my share of trouble with them, breaking not just one, but two <a href="http://joby.com/gorillapod/gorillapod-hybrid">Hybrid</a>&rsquo;s during the last couple of years. A leg falling off in both cases, they were warranted by <a href="https://joby.com">Joby</a>, and today the Hybrid is still my go-to tripod for outdoors.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/31861482020/in/photostream/" title="Three tools"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/1/777/31861482020_d698e5630f_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Three threads"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>In addition to Joby, I have also held onto a <a href="http://www.industrialrev.com/ultrapod-i.html">Pedco Ultrapod I</a>. A superlight and small, and cheap, yet sturdy tripod, it has even held a full frame DSLR without flinching. And with the included velcro strap one can easily secure a smaller camera on a tree branch or similar sketchy platform. Third tripod I have is actually one without legs, the <a href="https://trailpix.myshopify.com">TrailPix Ultralight Tripod</a>. I got this off <a href="https://www.kickstarter.com/projects/1312251870/trailpix-ultralight-tripod">Kickstarter</a> back in 2013, but it hasn&rsquo;t really been used much.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/31410611684/in/datetaken/" title="Pedco Ultrapod I"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/1/610/31410611684_f66663cc18_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1536" alt="Pedco Ultrapod I"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The reason is mainly that in addition to utilizing two <em>short</em> poles you ought to have with you, it still needs a third one, typically a spare pole (if you carry one) or a separate aluminum pole. Of course a wooden stick would do as well. I have poles when going (telemark) skiing, cross country or nordic skating poles are simply too long if you consider the need for a third one, and on some of the longer hikes, but most of hiking, paddling, climbing and whatnot is done without any poles. So, while the product is actually very good, with legs locked in place with screws and a solid <a href="http://en.cnkingjoy.com/en/products.asp?id=145">Kingjoy BD-1</a> ballhead included, for me it&rsquo;s not a very convenient product to use. But mainly for the (removable) ballhead, I still hold on to it.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/32132807051/in/photostream/" title="TrailPix"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/1/264/32132807051_3b0efc7a64_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1536" alt="TrailPix"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>TrailPix aside, none of the above easily bring the camera higher up, or help take the camera further than an arms length, should you hold it in your hands. Years ago, around the time first GoPro&rsquo;s came out, I had been for some time wanting something taller/longer to screw a camera onto. Considering a monopod, I was also browsing the limited range of trekking poles meant for photographers. I quickly ditched the idea of a dedicated monopod as it would just have been another thing to carry. And having a perfectly good set of poles for different uses, it seemed wasteful to get another pair just to attach a camera to. Why not simply add a threaded bolt to an existing pole and be done with it?</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/31861478980/in/album-72157677052503772/" title="Gibron and Black Diamond handles"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/1/286/31861478980_ec88a3e556_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Gibron and Black Diamond handles"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>From idea to action, a visit to the local nuts and bolts specialty store (as the needed &frac14;-20 UNC threaded screws are not standard items in a typical hardware store in Finland) soon had me pulling off the handle on my Gibron Sherpa II telescopic pole. A pre-drilled hole through the top of the handle helped to screw in the threaded bolt from the inside of the handle, fixed in place with a knob of hot glue. Threaded through just the right amount to not bottom out on the camera, it worked perfectly.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/31861483160/in/photostream/" title="Gibron Sherpa II"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/261/31861483160_3b937015e0_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Gibron Sherpa II"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>For example the below video was shot using this pole and a GoPro, strapped on the bow, extending a meter or so outside of the canoe.</p>

<iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/31107186" width="770" height="433" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>As the Sherpa&rsquo;s were my skiing poles, I&rsquo;ve used them a lot as a monopod for family and group photos in the winter. Sticking a pole into firm snow, with a small(ish) camera threaded in, is solid enough to trust on, unless there&rsquo;s hard wind. In those cases I&rsquo;ve typically piled some snow around it, or pushed it in deeper, sometimes removing the basket. With the GoPro&rsquo;s coming into play, threading one at the end of the pole has been a fun way to shoot one another skiing down the slopes, being able to reach out close enough for interesting angles. And of course it works like charm for including yourself, but also more of the surroundings, in the picture or a video reportage, despite not having an ultra wide angle lens.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/31427092363/in/photostream/" title="Black Diamond Distance Carbon Z handle"><img src="https://c4.staticflickr.com/1/570/31427092363_6b0b1d9d10_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Black Diamond Distance Carbon Z handle"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve since then done a similar work on two other pairs of poles I regularly use, both from Black Diamond. Traverse poles, great poles for ski touring by the way, were done the same way as the Gibron, first removing the handle by heating it - use hot water or a blow dryer. The strap comes off by pushing out a pin that locks it down, and it needs to be removed for drilling and threading in the bolt. It&rsquo;s a tight fit, but worked out fine, and once the bolt is securely in place, the strap can be re-attached without a fuzz. I opted to thread a nut on top, slightly recessed, which again was secured with a drop of hot glue.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/32103027202/in/dateposted/" title="Few tools required"><img src="https://c3.staticflickr.com/1/279/32103027202_d36e8b8fd2_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Few tools required"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Latest modification was done on a pair of <a href="http://blackdiamondequipment.com/en/trekking-poles/distance-carbon-flz-pole-BD112176_cfg.html#sz=24&amp;start=30">Distance Carbon FLZ Trekking Poles</a> I had gotten for my trip to <a href="http://leftbound.com/blog/2015/07/13/Iceland-Revisited/">Iceland</a>, requiring a slightly different approach. I could not get the handles off from these, most likely since, made of EVA foam, they appear to be glued in. Being ultralight poles, the wrist straps are not bolted in, but are held by a string of nylon running though the handle, past the midpoint. As I couldn&rsquo;t remove it, and didn&rsquo;t want to accidentally cut it, I had to place the bolt way up front, and not being able to remove the handle and thread it in from below, the bolt had to go in head first from the top. Being made of soft foam, I just pre-drilled a large enough hole into the soft handle to squeece the bolt in. After dry testing, I pushed hot glue into the hole, and in went the bolt, EVA stretching out as needed for a snug fit.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/32199117536/in/photostream/" title="Black Diamond Distance Carbon Z"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/261/32199117536_b5340cb84e_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Black Diamond Distance Carbon FLZ"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>As you can see in the photo, I used a nut here as well, mainly due to the softness of the handle - this way, and with the hot glue filling, the assembly was secure and solid, not giving in at all. Used since last autumn, also this pole has worked well as a make-do monopod, and with my new pyramid tent, the pair will get out even more in the future. Quite a versatile piece of kit they have turned out to be - from trekking poles to amonopod to an adjustable center pole!</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/31396369534/in/album-72157677052503772/" title="Flood happened"><img src="https://c7.staticflickr.com/1/368/31396369534_08da1a2518_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Flood happened"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve mentioned GoPro, which can easily be connected to the pole with the Tripod Mount accessory, but similarly you can use many other accessories to hook up whatever recording device you need, including your mobile phone. My iPhone 6 never leaves the protective <a href="https://www.catalystlifestyle.com/collections/iphone6/products/copy-of-catalyst-case-for-iphone-6-black-space-gray">Catalyst Case</a>, and I&rsquo;ve got a <a href="https://www.catalystlifestyle.com/collections/frontpage/products/iphone-6-plus-6s-plus-multi-sport-mount">Multi-Sport Mount</a> to lock it down securely to any of my monopod poles.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/31861475980/in/album-72157677052503772/" title="GoPro Tripod Mount"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/1/568/31861475980_6b2add6471_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="GoPro Tripod Mount"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/31875538220/in/album-72157677052503772/" title="Multi-Sport Mount from Catalyst"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/1/541/31875538220_2237120d44_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Multi-Sport Mount from Catalyst"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Needless to say, these have been extremely useful modifications for me, and relatively simple to do, I can recommend them to anyone. If you already have a good pair of poles, I see no reason to invest into a new pair just to get the tripod mount. Not having to unscrew anything is a big plus in my books, as opposed to removable caps and whatnot seen on some of the dedicated products, essentially offering the same functionality in a bit more polished, though maybe over-engineered, package.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/32199118316/in/album-72157677052503772/" title="Three mounts"><img src="https://c5.staticflickr.com/1/392/32199118316_0acadef9f9_k.jpg" width="2048" height="1365" alt="Three mounts"></a><script async src="//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>&#10095;&#10095; Flickr album: <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/albums/72157677052503772">MYOG - Monopod Pole</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Canon 5D]]></title>
    <link href="http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2014/11/26/Canon-5D/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-26T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2014/11/26/Canon-5D</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Long live the DSLR!</p>

<p>Despite various micro four thirds and other mirrorless systems, digital single lens reflex cameras are still hugely popular also amongst consumers and prosumers, especially APS-C sized DSLRs flying off the shelves. Reasons can be debated, but for me, having stepped down from a film SLR (Canon EOS 5 at the time, with the neat eye controlled focusing) to a more or less pocketable cameras and camera systems when digital picked up, DSLR represents uncompromized control and handling (on top of suberb image quality of course). Therefore, despite the bulk and vast array of mirrorless systems (some of which I&rsquo;ve tested), I&rsquo;ve been drawn to it time and again. Despite my constant graving, I never bought one before last year, picking up a Canon 6D - the most affordable full frame body to date.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>While 6D, coupled with some good lenses, is super, I struggled to justify the cost of the system compared to how much time it spent on the shelf. Being left behind because of the size and weight too many times, I sold it after 9 months to look into some other, more pocketable, and a lot cheaper, options. Suppressing the creeping feeling of regret, I found a good deal on Fujifilm S100s and gave it a go for a short while. I tested also the mirrorless Sony A7 briefly, through a friend, but found the handling inferior to my liking and size/weight too close to a DSLR to get interested - not to mention the steep price. Image quality was no doubt excellent, with all the full frame benefits.</p>

<p>After some time mostly using my iPhone and the very good Canon S100 pocketable, for the day-to-day photos, Canon 5D, the first version, hiding in plain sight, caught my attention. Released in late 2005, this first professional quality, reasonably priced (as opposed to 7000 EUR for 1D) full frame body attracted lots of professionals and prosumers alike, priced at around 3000 EUR at the time of release.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157648982004329/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7537/15842405062_b3ffcdfc6e_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Due to the age, and subsequent releases of MKII and MKIII, the price of second-hand 5D is currently only around 500 EUR, depending on the condition and especially the shutter count, rated at 100000 by Canon. I paid 420 EUR for mine, in excellent condition, including a BG-E4 battery grip, with a modest (confirmed) shutter count just shy of 18000. A steal in my opinion, I coupled it with another classic, nifty fifty, 50mm f/1.8 mkII boasting a large aperture and great image quality, though pretty soft until stopped at 2.8, generally available around 100 EUR as new.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157648982004329/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7502/15657263257_01a30c83e2_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>While 5D is lacking some of the useful features newer DSLR&rsquo;s (and especially 5D MKII and MKIII) have, such as the automatic sensor cleaning, live view, weather protection and video, and has modest amount of megapixels in current standards, it gives a lot of bang for the buck in a solid magnesium frame. Not competitive at high ISOs (5D&rsquo;s range ends at 6400, and is clean enough up to around 1600 - when for example 6D can be pushed to 12800, even 25600 with comparable results), the output from the 12.8 MP sensor is balanced with good tonality. And while already at ISO 800 noise is evident, output is still beautiful in my opinion, and many newer cameras fare a lot worse.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157648982004329/"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7583/15842465162_f13cbac5fd_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>It has been great to find out that an eight year old camera can still hold its own in a digital world where next generation tends to outplay the previous one tenfold.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/jonipalomaki/sets/72157648982004329/"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8612/15223431893_9916ce9f39_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Having had it now for few weeks, I haven&rsquo;t found any issues to speak off and it&rsquo;s been effortless to use (as an old Canon user). But if you are considering to buy one, there are couple of known issues you might want to check. One of them is the <a href="http://www.usa.canon.com/cusa/support/consumer?pageKeyCode=prdAdvDetail&amp;docId=0901e0248004cd94">attachment of mirror, which Canon has luckily warrantied</a> - most of the bodies in the market should hence have it already fixed. And in any case the the problem is related to hot and humid environments only, where the mirror could, in some cases, come loose. The fix is a re-glue or additional clips on the sides of the mirror - if in doubt, drop the camera off to a service for checkup.</p>

<p>The other known issue is a small batch of LCD on cameras with serial number starting with 1 (made in 2006), which can have a greenish tint or cast in them, something that apparently has also been plaguing the LCDs on MK II. Also notice that there is no way to get the exact shutter count out of the camera yourself (image counter in the menu can be manually reset, and resets automatically at 10000, so cannot be used as a reference), but Canon service can pull that out for you easily. Mine is from the first batch, serial number starting with 0, and has no discoloration, though one must realize LCDs have gone a long way since 2005 - you better delete photos only when viewed at the computer.</p>

<p>When planning to buy one, I found for example <a href="http://www.virtualtraveller.org/5dii/5dii.htm">this comparison with MK II</a> useful for decision making, and you can find an overview and specs for example at <a href="http://www.kenrockwell.com/canon/5d.htm">kenrockwell.com</a> or <a href="http://www.dpreview.com/reviews/canoneos5d">dpreview.com</a>, while <a href="http://www.ephotozine.com/article/canon-eos-5d-mark-i-vs-ii-vs-iii-review-comparison-19775">ephotozine.com</a> has done some comparisons between the three 5D versions.</p>

<p>At the moment I have no plans to purchase more lenses as I try to keep it lean and cheap (unless some crazy deal comes around) but I had been looking for a waterproof bag and eyeballing especially the <a href="http://www.ortlieb.com/_prod.php?lang=en&amp;produkt=vshot">Ortlieb V-Shot</a>. Come today, I noticed <a href="https://varuste.net/Ortlieb+V-shot?_tu=49302">Varuste.net</a> had 20% off on all Ortlieb bags, so jumped on it and picked up the last one from the store after work. A long time user of Ortlieb gear, I have no doubt it can take a beating and will keep the camera safe, backed up with a 5-year warranty.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Autumn Tones]]></title>
    <link href="http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2013/10/09/Autumn-Tones/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-09T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://leftbound.com/leftbound/blog/2013/10/09/Autumn-Tones</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Autumn rocks, period. Crisp weather, colorful foliage and light like no other. And absolutely no reason to stay indoors.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157641624227453/"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2806/12800784915_fb976a4b8c_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<!-- more -->


<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157641624227453/"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7410/12800779995_f9caf6c34a_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157641624227453/"><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7438/12801202994_8cc94b7497_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/67976808@N06/sets/72157641624227453/"><img src="http://farm3.staticflickr.com/2893/12800786325_a9004d75bd_b.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
